<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://cwrc.ca/schemas/cwrc_tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://cwrc.ca/templates/css/cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cw="http://cwrc.ca/ns/cw#">
        <rdf:Description rdf:about="http://localhost:8080/editor/documents/null">
            <cw:mode>0</cw:mode>
        </rdf:Description>
    </rdf:RDF>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Blank Document</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc sameAs="http://www.cwrc.ca">
                <p>Created from original research by members of CWRC/CSÉC unless otherwise noted.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <head>
                    <title>Sample Letter - Bertrand Russell to <persName annotationId="ent_73" cert="probable" ref="279399399">Patricia Spence</persName> - October 21, 1935</title>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <note annotationId="ent_91">
                        <p>Bad writing due to shaky train</p><p>In train</p><p>
                            <placeName annotationId="ent_71" cert="definite">Oslo</placeName> to Bergen</p>
                    </note>
                    <dateline>
                        <date annotationId="ent_69" cert="definite" when="1935-10-21">21.10.35</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dearest -</salute>
                </opener><p>I have had no letter from you since I left <placeName annotationId="ent_67" cert="definite">Stockholm</placeName>, but I had a nice one from John in an envelope you had sent him. I had sent him one addressed to Copenhagen but he hadn't used it.</p><p>When I reached Oslo yesterday evening, Brynjulf Bull should have been there to meet me, but wasn't. He is not on the telephone, so I took a taxi to his address, which turned out to be a students' club with no one about on Sundays, so I went to a hotel feeling rather non-plussed. But presently he turned up. He had got the <pb n="2"/> time of my arrival wrong, and 
                        <corr annotationId="ent_65">when</corr>
                    he had found he had missed me he phoned to every hotel in Oslo till he hit on the right one. He left me at 10, and then I had to do a Sunday Referee article. Today my journey lasts from 9 till 9 - fortunately one of the most beautiful railway journeys in the world. Tomorrow I lecture at <placeName annotationId="ent_63" cert="probable" ref="5">Bergen</placeName> to the Anglo-Norwegian Society. Next day I go back to Oslo, lecture there Fri. and Sat. and then start for home via Bergen.</p>
                <pb n="3"/>
                <p>Bull is a nice young man but incompetent - can't quite stand the communists, but finds the socialists too mild.</p><p>I am unhappily wondering what you are feeling about me.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I love you very much -</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName sameAs="http://www.freebase.com/view/en/bertrand_russell">
                            <persName annotationId="ent_109" cert="definite" type="real" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/36924137">B</persName>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
