<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- common schema   *in progress*
    for use by Biography, Events and Writing schemas
    written 2010-03-31 by Mariana Paredes-Olea,
    based on events.dtd and biograph.dtd (SGML)
    Copyright 2010 The Orlando Project -->

<!-- Revision as of 2011-01-16 -->

<!-- TO DO:-->
<!--Check SGML minimization rules that allow for non-closed tags:
    xptr , xref-->
<!-- Redefine default values - schematron -->
<!-- Check inclusions and exclusions -->
<!-- check all mixed patterns against dtds (text) -->

<grammar xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
    xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0"
    xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"    
    datatypeLibrary="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes"
    >

    <start>
        <ref name="Events-element"></ref>
    </start>
    
    <!-- Chronstruct does not accept bibcit/s
        in event submission database, this is a variation of chronstruct to
        restrict use ob bibcit/s (only for events)-->
    <define name="chronStruct-element">   
        <element name="CHRONSTRUCT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">A chronStruct is an element that holds together and therefore associates a date with the prose that describes an event.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>Definition</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>A chronStruct is an element that holds together and therefore associates a date with the prose that describes an event.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h2>Placement</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>A chronStruct can only contain sub-elements. You are not permitted to type directly into this element. A chronStruct can only include one date, dateRange, or dateStruct to be followed by a chronProse. Although you may not include two dates in the chronStruct, you are allowed to use the date element again the chronProse if needed.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h2>Relationships</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>In events documents a chronStruct is contained by a chronEvent. In biography documents, it can appear inside a Div1--content tag such as birth or death, or inside a Div2 or Div3. In writing documents, a chronStruct can appear inside a Div2--production, Div2--reception, or Div2--textualFeatures or inside a Div3. In biography and writing documents, please insert a chronStruct at the level that is most appropriate to research you are tagging. Every chronStruct no matter which document it appears in contains a date followed by a chronProse. Both these sub-elements are required. chronStruct is modified by the required chronColumn attribute in events documents.</xhtml:p>              
            <xhtml:h2>Examples</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;NATIONALINTERNATIONAL&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;July 1832&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;&lt;The Friends of the Oppressed established by a group of politically active London women.&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;NATIONALINTERNATIONAL&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;1 April 1905&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;&lt;Penny Post was available one way from the United Kingdom to Australia&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h2>Practice Issues</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>Because chronStructs may be removed from the documents in which they were created and be placed alongside unrelated information, always make sure that you put enough information in a chronStruct such that it will make sense when read out of context. Make sure that any important names, dates, places, or orgNames are tagged inside a chronStruct. Also, do not use pronouns in a chronStruct unless their referent is also present.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"></ref>
            <optional>
                <ref name="chronColumn-attributes"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <ref name="relevance-attributes"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <ref name="resp-content"/>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <group>
                    <choice>
                        <ref name="dateRange-element"></ref>
                        <ref name="dateStruct-element"></ref>
                        <ref name="date-element"></ref>
                    </choice>
                    <ref name="chronProse-element"></ref>
                </group>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion-noBibcits"></ref>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"></ref>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="Common">
        <!-- check -->
        <ref name="OrlandoHeader-element"/>
    </define>

	<define name="Div0-inclusion-noBibcits">
        <zeroOrMore>
            <choice>
                <ref name="researchNote-element"></ref>
                <ref name="title-element"></ref>
                <ref name="scholarNote-element"></ref>
                <ref name="keywordClass-element"></ref>
                <ref name="lb-element"></ref>
            </choice>
        </zeroOrMore>
    </define>
    
    <define name="Events-element">
        <element name="EVENTS">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Events is the largest element available in events documents and its sole purpose is to contain the overall document structure.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>Definition</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>Events is the largest element available in events documents and its sole purpose is to contain the overall document structure.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h2>Placement</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h2>Relationships</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>Events is the first element inserted in an events document. It contains the OrlandoHeader and at least one Div0. It has no unique attributes.</xhtml:p>
            <optional>
                <ref name="ID-attribute"></ref>
            </optional>
            <ref name="OrlandoHeader-element"></ref>
            <oneOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-element"></ref>
            </oneOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <!-- OrlandoHeader starts -->

    <define name="OrlandoHeader-element">
        <element name="ORLANDOHEADER">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Equivalent to TEI's TEIHeader, OrlandoHeader supplies the descriptive and declarative information making up an electronic title page prefixed to every TEI-conformant text.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>OrlandoHeader</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Equivalent to TEI's TEIHeader, OrlandoHeader supplies the descriptive and declarative information making up an electronic title page prefixed to every TEI-conformant text.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;ORLANDOHEADER TYPE="text"&gt;&lt;FILEDESC&gt;&lt;TITLESTMT&gt;&lt;DOCTITLE&gt;Winifred Maxwell, Countess of Nithsdale: writing&lt;/DOCTITLE&gt;&lt;/TITLESTMT&gt;&lt;PUBLICATIONSTMT&gt;&lt;AUTHORITY&gt;Orlando Project&lt;/AUTHORITY&gt;&lt;/PUBLICATIONSTMT&gt;&lt;SOURCEDESC&gt;Based on original research by members of the Orlando Project.&lt;/SOURCEDESC&gt;&lt;/FILEDESC&gt;&lt;REVISIONDESC&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="MPO" WORKSTATUS="SUB" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;21 October 2011&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;Initial document given to tagger.&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;/REVISIONDESC&gt;&lt;/ORLANDOHEADER&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional> <!-- check in dtd -->
                <attribute name="TYPE" a:defaultValue="TEXT"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="fileDesc-element"/>
            <optional>
                <ref name="revisionDesc-element"/>
            </optional>            
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="fileDesc-element">
        <element name="FILEDESC">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">fileDesc contains a full bibliographic description of an electronic file.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>fileDesc</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>fileDesc contains a full bibliographic description of an electronic file.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;FILEDESC&gt;&lt;TITLESTMT&gt;&lt;DOCTITLE&gt;Rose Allatini: biography&lt;/DOCTITLE&gt;&lt;/TITLESTMT&gt;&lt;PUBLICATIONSTMT&gt;&lt;AUTHORITY&gt;Orlando Project&lt;/AUTHORITY&gt;&lt;/PUBLICATIONSTMT&gt;&lt;SOURCEDESC&gt;Created from original research by members of the Orlando Project&lt;/SOURCEDESC&gt;&lt;/FILEDESC&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <ref name="titleStmt-element"/>
            <optional>
                <ref name="docExtent-element"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="publicationStmt-element"/>
            <ref name="sourceDesc-element"/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="titleStmt-element">
        <element name="TITLESTMT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">titleStmt groups information about the title of a work and those responsible for its intellectual content.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>titleStmt</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>titleStmt groups information about the title of a work and those responsible for its intellectual content.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;TITLESTMT&gt;&lt;DOCTITLE&gt;Rose Allatini: biography&lt;/DOCTITLE&gt;&lt;/TITLESTMT&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <group>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <ref name="docTitle-element"/>
                </oneOrMore>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <element name="DOCAUTHOR">
                            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
                            <text/>
                        </element>
                        <element name="DOCEDITOR">
                            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
                            <attribute name="ROLE" a:defaultValue="EDITOR"> </attribute>
                            <text/>
                        </element>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
            </group>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="docTitle-element">
        <element name="DOCTITLE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">DocTitle is an element in the OrlandoHeader that contains the title of the document at hand for cataloguing purposes. This title will be in the template for most of the documents created on the Orlando Project, but will need to be filled in for certain documents, such as events documents and documents created without a template.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>docTitle</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>DocTitle is an element in the OrlandoHeader that contains the title of the document at hand for cataloguing purposes. This title will be in the template for most of the documents created on the Orlando Project, but will need to be filled in for certain documents, such as events documents and documents created without a template.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>docTitle is contained within the fileDesc--titleStmt area of the OrlandoHeader. It contains no sub-elements and has one attribute, type, which we are currently not using in conjunction with this element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Lucy Aiken: writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Lucy Aiken: biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Censorship: 1890-1960</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>British Broadcasting Corporation Chronology</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Although events documents have their docTitle element filled in, these documents and their titles are only temporary. Eventually each document will be broken down into its component chronEvents and will lose it overarching title. In the meantime, please give your events documents titles that are indicative of their content so as to help other project members find the information you have entered in anticipation of the day when each chronStruct will be databased separately.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="TYPE"/>
            </optional>
            <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                    <text/>
                    <ref name="date-element"/>
                    <ref name="emph-element"/>
                    <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                    <ref name="soCalled-element"/>
                    <ref name="quote-element"/>
                    <ref name="rs-element"/>
                </choice>
            </zeroOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="date-element">
        <element name="DATE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Date is one of three elements, along with dateRange and dateStruct, used to systematize the capture of dates across project documents. Date is used to tag all singular dates (not ranges) for which all components (day, month, year) have a common degree of certainty. <xhtml:br/>Accurate and systematic tagging of dates on the project is a high priority both for the role that dates play in sorting and properly displaying chronology events, but also for facilitating the search and retrieval of non-chronology material across project documents.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>date</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Date is one of three elements, along with dateRange and dateStruct, used to systematize the capture of dates across project documents. Date is used to tag all singular dates (not ranges) for which all components (day, month, year) have a common degree of certainty.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Accurate and systematic tagging of dates on the project is a high priority both for the role that dates play in sorting and properly displaying chronology events, but also for facilitating the search and retrieval of non-chronology material across project documents.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>A date tag should be placed around only that information that is part of the date itself. Surrounding prose and punctuation should be, by and large, kept outside the date element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Date can occur anywhere that it is valid to type text in your document (i.e. in paragraphs, chronStructs, and dataItems). One of date, dateRange, or dateStruct is required in each chronStruct. It has the following attributes: calendar, certainty, and value.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date&gt;1844&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date&gt;May 1765&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date&gt;14 July 1913&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date VALUE=&quot;1682-10-&quot; CERTAINTY=&quot;C&quot;&gt;Late 1682&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>By the &lt;date VALUE=&quot;1967-09-21&quot; CERTAINTY=&quot;BY&quot;&gt;21st of September&lt;/&gt;, the petition had 50,000 signatures.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Whenever possible, put dates in standard form within your date element. The standard form for written dates is day, month, year (12 May 1997). When putting a date in standard written form, do not worry about adding a 0 to single digit numbers (9 April 1914). If you do not want to express a date in standard form for reasons of style, make sure you provide a standard expression for the date in a value attribute. Here, dates are expressed numerically as year, month day (1997-05-12). Please see value for more information about using the value attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you do not have the day or month on which an event occurred, enter what you have of the date. The following dates do not need to be standardised in the value attribute:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date&gt;1844&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date&gt;May 1765&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date&gt;14 July 1913&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag all dates. Use your best judgement in determining which dates are relevant to your document but as a general rule, only tag dates that are significant to a person&apos;s life and writing or an historical event. For example, if a woman writer received a letter of acceptance from a publisher or received news of a family member&apos;s death, tag the date; if she received routine correspondence from a friend or family member, mention the date but do not tag it.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag the same date twice in one document or chronStruct unless it refers to two logically separate events.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag dates within biography and writing documents that refer to general world events rather than the participation of the particular person with these events. General world events should be tagged elsewhere. For example, in Vera Brittain&apos;s biography document, the date on which her brother was killed in World War 1 should be tagged. The day on which the war ended, should be tagged elsewhere as a chronology event and need not be tagged in the biography document as well.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p><b>Checklist:</b> Make sure that each date you tag conforms to the following practice checklist</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>if you did not need to use a value attribute or if you are just checking the text of the date, check to make sure format is correct: 7 January 1898 (the date can be truncated from the left but not from the right). Are they any typos? Remove leading 0 in single digit text dates.</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>if you are checking the value attribute, make sure format is correct: 1983-01-10, 1983-01-, 1983--. Make sure leading 0 is present for single digit months and days. Make sure both hyphens are present. Add text to tag if it is missing (especially in chronStruct)</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>where necessary, move spaces/punctuation (or add spaces) outside tag to ensure doc reads properly</xhtml:li>   
                <xhtml:li>remove any bibCits in the tag and place them in the appropriate place</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>remove any research notes from inside the tag and place them just outside the end tag (or delete it they are trivial and the problem has been fixed)</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>remove any empty date tags except in files that are template only--fix doc where necessary if this makes the doc invalid</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>In order to determine whether or not a date should be captured inside a date element, ask yourself the following questions: If I am inside a chronstruct in an Events document, is the date I want to tag the one on which the chronology event occurred? If I am inside a chronstruct in a Biography or Writing document, does the date I want to tag refer to an event the subject was involved in?</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: When should I use date and when should I use dateStruct? Answer: Most often you will want to use the date element over the dateStruct element. However, if you are certain an event occurred in a certain year but you are unsure of the day or month on which the event occurred, you will want to use a dateStruct to express differing degrees of certainty to the components that make up a date. You will also on occasion wish to mark the exact time of day on which an event occurred. dateStruct has a mechanism to allow this information to be captured.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: I want to tag a date, but the problem is that I don&apos;t have a definite date because my sources disagree. It&apos;s one of two dates: either Date A or Date B. Answer: You will need to use your judgement here to decide which source you think most reliable and tag the date that you think best. You can then discuss the scholarly discrepancy in a scholar&apos;s note.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date CERTAINTY=&quot;unknown&quot;&gt;24 September 1713&lt;/&gt;&lt;scholarNote&gt;CriticA suggests that the event might have occured on the 22nd.&lt;/&gt; or</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;date VALUE=&quot;1713-09-24&quot; CERTAINTY=&quot;unknown&quot;&gt;22 or 24 September 1713&lt;/&gt;&lt;scholarNote&gt;CriticA suggests that the event occured on the 22nd, but the Grundy biography offers evidence for the 25th.&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <!-- SRF: Is this what unknown is meant to capture? -->
            <xhtml:p>In both these examples, the date will be sorted for chronology by the value attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="date-attributes"/>
            <interleave>
                <text/>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <!-- Inclusion from Div1 and Div0 except elements
                    in DTD exclusion (dateStruct, dateRange, keywordClass,
                    name, orgName, place, scholarNote, topic) Bio also excludes-->
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="date-attributes">
        <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
        <ref name="calendar-content"/>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="VALUE"/>
        </optional>
        <ref name="certainty-content"/>
    </define>

    <define name="calendar-content">
        <optional>
            <attribute name="CALENDAR" a:defaultValue="NEWSTYLE">
                <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">An attribute of date, dateRange, and dateStruct, calendar is used to indicate when a given date took place.</a:documentation>
                <xhtml:h2>calendar</xhtml:h2>
                <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>An attribute of date, dateRange, and dateStruct, calendar is used to indicate when a given date took place.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>Calendar is an optional attribute of date, dateRange, and dateStruct. It has values of &quot;newStyle&quot; and &quot;BC&quot;.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;date CALENDAR=&quot;NewStyle&quot;&gt;2 January 1656&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <choice>
                    <value>NEWSTYLE</value>
                    <value>BC</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
    </define>

    <define name="certainty-content">
        <!-- mp: check if certainty , calendar are optional attributes. -->
        <optional>
            <attribute name="CERTAINTY" a:defaultValue="CERT">
                <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Certainty is an attribute of date, dateRange, and dateStruct and is used to indicate the nature of certainty that you have about a given date.</a:documentation>
                <xhtml:h2>certainty</xhtml:h2>
                <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>Certainty is an attribute of date, dateRange, and dateStruct and is used to indicate the nature of certainty that you have about a given date.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>An attribute of date, dateRange, and dateStruct, certainty has values of &quot;cert&quot; (certain), &quot;c&quot; (circa), &quot;by,&quot; &quot;after,&quot; &quot;unknown,&quot; and &quot;roughlyDated.&quot;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>LF&apos;s mother died on &lt;date CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;21 November 1933&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>At the &lt;date CERTAINTY=&quot;c&quot; VALUE=&quot;1939&quot;&gt;outbreak of the second world war&lt;/&gt;, GH was a nurse in London.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>When she returned from Paris in &lt;date CERTAINTY=&quot;after&quot;1863&lt;/&gt;, she began working as a governess.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>The default value for this attribute is &quot;cert,&quot; meaning that the date is (to the best of all knowledge) fixed and accurate. If the date you are tagging is certain, you do not need to fill in the certainty attribute. Assume this default if your sources assert a specific date without pointing to any historical/scholarly debate over the date&apos;s accuracy.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&quot;c&quot; equals circa and is used to indicate an approximate date.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&quot;by&quot; and &quot;after&quot; are used when you can positively assert that an event occurred by or after a given date, but when you are unable to pinpoint a more certain date. These attributes are often used when your source gives a person&apos;s age for a date rather than the date itself.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;date CERTAINTY=&quot;by&quot; VALUE=&quot;1825--&quot;&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>In this example, the tagger knows that the British woman writer was born in 1911, but does not know a specific date for the move to Bristol. Simple math indicates that the BWW would turn thirteen in 1924; therefore by the end of 1925, she must have moved to Bristol.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&quot;unknown&quot; indicates that an event can&apos;t be dated with certainty.</xhtml:p>
                <!-- SRF: Not sure I know when it is appropriate to use this value -->
                <xhtml:p>&quot;roughlyDated&quot; is an attribute value properly used only within the dateRange element. It is meant to indicate a specific, undated event that occurred sometime during a specified span of time. For example, if we knew that Elizabeth Barrett Browning moved to Italy sometime in the 1870s, we would not want to say that she moved to Italy from 1870-1880. Rather we would want to approximately or roughly date what is a singular event. Practice will be to use roughly dated only when a general range is known for a specific date.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>She met William Godwin in the &lt;dateRange CERTAINTY=&quot;roughlyDated&quot;&lt;1890s&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Dates, Uncertainty, and Book Reviews:</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>&quot;By&quot; and &quot;after&quot; are popular choices when dating the publications of book using their review date. If a book is reviewed on 17 July 1877, we can be fairly sure it was published by then. In this case, be sure to use the word &quot;by&quot; in your prose as well.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>If you are referencing an advertisement for a book (one that says &quot;just ready&quot; or &quot;today published&quot;) use the after attribute. In the eighteenth century, for example, &quot;this day published&quot; could be used to proclaim the novelty of the book for several weeks after its publication, so if you are using newspaper sources, beware, and use the &quot;after&quot; attribute. If, however, you are using the work of a trusted scholar, you might be more &quot;certain&quot; about trusting her assertation of the publication date based on an ad, but you should still use the &quot;circa&quot; attribute.</xhtml:p>
                <choice>
                    <value>CERT</value>
                    <a:documentation>Certain</a:documentation>
                    <value>C</value>
                    <a:documentation>Circa</a:documentation>
                    <value>BY</value>
                    <a:documentation>By this date</a:documentation>
                    <value>AFTER</value>
                    <a:documentation>After this date</a:documentation>
                    <value>UNKNOWN</value>
                    <a:documentation>Unknown date</a:documentation>
                    <value>ROUGHLYDATED</value>
                    <a:documentation>Rough certainty</a:documentation>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
    </define>

    <define name="emph-element">
        <element name="EMPH">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Short for emphasis, emph is an element that marks words or phrases which are stressed or emphasized for linguistic or rhetorical effect.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>emph</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Short for emphasis, emph is an element that marks words or phrases which are stressed or emphasized for linguistic or rhetorical effect.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Emph surrounds only those words that should be set apart typographically from surrounding text.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Emph is available from the Div1 level on down and should be used only in those places where typing is allowed (i.e. headings, chronProse, dataItems, and shortProse). It has no required sub-elements or unique attributes.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Eliza Fenwick, who had recently decided &lt;emph&gt;not&lt;/&gt; to join her daughter in Barbados, embarked with her son on the two-month voyage there.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>In the following example emphasis is marked as coming from the original source, a letter from Mary Taylor to Charlotte Brontë:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&quot;You talk of women working. And this first duty, this necessity you seem to think that &lt;emph&gt;some&lt;/&gt; women may indulge in -- if they give up marriage and don&apos;t make themselves too disagreeable to the other sex. You are a coward and a traitor. A woman who works is by that alone better than one who does not.&quot;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Emph will likely be used very rarely in project documents. Designed for the TEI, emph is best used by projects recording pre-existing texts where words have been emphasized by typography but the encoder has no indication of why the words have been set off. If you are considering using the emph element, please consult the documentation for the foreign, rs, socalled, and title elements to ensure that your purposes are not better served by one of these elements.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="rs-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="corr-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="emph-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="foreign-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="soCalled-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="quote-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/>-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="foreign-element">
        <element name="FOREIGN">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The foreign element identifies a word or phrase as belonging to some language other than that of the surrounding text.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>foreign</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The foreign element identifies a word or phrase as belonging to some language other than that of the surrounding text.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Foreign surrounds only those words that are part of the foreign language.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Foreign is available from the Div1 level on down and should be used only in those places where typing is allowed (i.e. headings, chronProse, dataItems, and shortProse). It has two unique attributes, lang (i.e. language), where the language of the word or phrase marked can be typed, and reg, where if necessary or possible, a translation of the foreign phrase can be provided. Foreign has no required sub-elements, although it is permissible for other globally available elements (i.e. name or orgName) to appear within it.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>AD received high praise from Berlioz. He is cited as having said of AD, &lt;foreign LANG=&quot;French&quot;&gt;Si elle ne s&apos;approchait pas, c&apos;est le piano qui marcherait vers elle&lt;/&gt;, and &lt;foreign LANG=&quot;French&quot;c&apos;est plus qu&apos;une musicienne, c&apos;est la mélodie&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;foreign LANG=&quot;French&quot; REG=&quot;pilot&apos;s licence&quot;&gt;brevet de pilote d&apos;aeroplane&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;foreign LANG="Gaelic" REG="House of Sorrow"&gt;Broin Bearg&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;foreign REG=&quot;Silent Ones&quot;&gt;Ekumeku&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>If using the foreign tag in addition to a title tag for the names of books, films etc., only give a translation when the English title is known--in other words, don&apos;t guess at a translation; if you don&apos;t know or the book has not been translated for books or the film subtitled or dubbed, then just leave the reg attribute empty.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not use the foreign tag around the names of political/parliamentary bodies and groups: eg., Sinn Fein, Cumann na mBan, Nazi party.</xhtml:p>
            <!-- kdc; this last one still under discussion March 99 -->
            <xhtml:p>Do not use a foreign element to denote foreign expressions that have entered common English usage such as, chic, en route, debutante, and panache. Other foreign words, such as Luftwaffe, blitzkreig, Krystalnacht, and Sinn Fein, will be recognizable in English but not part of English idiom. Tag these words with the foreign element but do not provide translations for them. If you are having trouble distinguishing between words that have entered idiom and those that have not, ask yourself the following question: &quot;if I were putting this word in an academic paper would I need to italicize it?&quot; If the answer is yes, then tag it; if the answer is no, then don&apos;t tag it.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>You do not have to use the reg attribute to provide translations of all foreign expressions. If, however, your source provides a translation, you may use the reg attribute to add this information.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="LANG"/>
            </optional>
            <!-- change to xml:lang ?-->
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="rs-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="corr-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="emph-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="foreign-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="soCalled-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="quote-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/>-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="soCalled-element">
        <element name="SOCALLED">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Socalled contains a word or phrase for which the author or narrator indicates a disclaiming of responsibility, for example by the use of scare quotes or italics.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>socalled</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Socalled contains a word or phrase for which the author or narrator indicates a disclaiming of responsibility, for example by the use of scare quotes or italics.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The socalled element should surround only those words which should be placed in scare quotes or italics.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>socalled is available from the Div1 level on down and should be used only in those places where typing is allowed (ie headings, chronProse, dataItems, and shortProse). It has no unique attributes or sub-elements.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>ALB took an approach that differed from that of the &lt;socalled&gt;great schools&lt;/&gt; in England at the time.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>LDG later underwent conflicted and confused feelings when she found out about Nana Sahib and Azimullah Khan&apos;s involvement in the killings of the 1857 &lt;socalled&gt;Indian Mutiny&lt;/&gt; in Cawnpore, especially since she sympathised with the natives against the English.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Although AG in general was opposed to the officiousness of &lt;socalled&gt;do-gooding&lt;/&gt; Female Societies, by 1818, she was involved with a organization promoting Gaelic schools.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>She is at pains to distinguish herself from the &lt;socalled&gt;lazy Creole&lt;/&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Periods, commas. semicolons, and colons generally go outside of the tag. When tagging a quotation, then the punctuation goes outside if your example is less than three words and inside the tag for examples containing four words or more.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag titles when a part of the phrase &quot;as Author of . . .&quot; when they occur in SoCalled tags in writing docs.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not use the soCalled tag in place of a quote tag for quotations within quotations; use instead the quote tag with attribute &quot;direct=N&quot; filled in.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do use the soCalled tag within the quote tag to set apart words mentioned (not used) in the original or words which the original author has distanced her-/himself from, has placed in scarequotes, or for which there is no single identifiable speaker (N.B. there are many instances in our tagging of these cases that have been tagged as &lt;quote direct=n&gt;within&lt;quote direct=n&gt;; these also should be cleaned up.)</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/>
                        <ref name="rs-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="corr-element"/>
                        <ref name="emph-element"/>
                        <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                        <ref name="soCalled-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/>-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="quote-element">
        <element name="QUOTE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The quote element is globally available and should be used wherever you quote a source.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>quote</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The quote element is globally available and should be used wherever you quote a source.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>           
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>This element is modified by one attribute, &quot;direct.&quot; The attribute options are yes (y), no (n), or unspecified (unspecified). These govern whether the quote will be represented with single or double quotes.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Do I need to use a quote element everytime I want to use quotation marks? Answer: Yes and no. You should not enter quotation marks in your documents whatsoever. Quotation marks will be supplied by the system for the quote element as well as for a few other elements such as analytic titles and words appearing in the socalled element. The following is a brief summary of practice around the proper use of the quote element. Each issue listed here is discussed in detail with examples below.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>A bibCit must follow every quote tag in bio and writing docs</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>A bibCit is optional following a quote tag in events</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Periods and commas should be placed inside the quote tag</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>bibCits following quotes should be spaced as if they were not part of the document</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>a person quoted from a source that she/he did not author must be referred to as "qtd. in" in the bibCit attributes</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>the direct attribute on quote should be filled in to &quot;y&quot; unless one quote tag is embedded inside another at which point the outer tag would be DIRECT=&quot;y&quot; and the inner tag would be DIRECT=&quot;n&quot;</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>page numbers in bibCits should not repeat numbers (e.g. 65-6 NOT 65-66)</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>See also &quot;soCalled.&quot;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Quotes and BibCits:All quote tags in bio/writing docs should be followed by a bibCit as if the sentence had normal spacing without the bibCit. The bibCit following a quote is optional in events, but it must be present at the level of the event.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>It was originally opened by Queen Victoria as the People&apos;s Palace, a place of &lt;quote Direct=y&gt;rational and instructive entertainment and of artistic enjoyment&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;bibcit&gt;Harte 174&lt;/bibcit&gt;for the people of East London.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Note: There is no space between the end of the quote and the beginning of the bibCit, but there is a space after the bibCit before the following word. For issues of punctuation other than commas, consult Jeanne Wood.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Unless: If a single source is quoted multiple times in one sentence, the bibCit should immediately follow the end of the sentence.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Linking alcohol to higher incidents of domestic abuse and violence, LA goes on to describe how the law favours men and disfavours women. She details two points on which &lt;QUOTE DIRECT=&quot;Y&quot;&gt;laws bear hard on women.&lt;/QUOTE&gt;&lt;BIBCIT Qtd. in = QtdInYes&gt; Le Breton 368-9&lt;/BIBCIT&gt; The first concerns the &lt;QUOTE DIRECT=&quot;Y&quot;&gt;want of a stricter hand against the inveiglers of girls for wicked purposes&lt;/QUOTE&gt;; the second deplores a man&apos;s right to child custody when his &lt;QUOTE DIRECT=&quot;Y&quot;&gt;offences have compelled an innocent wife to obtain a divorce from him.&lt;/QUOTE&gt;&lt;BIBCITqtd. in= QtdInYes&gt; Le Breton 368-9&lt;/BIBCIT&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If a person other than the author of the work cited in the bibCit is quoted then use the QtdInYes value on the attribute &quot;qtd. in&quot; found on the bibCit element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>According to literary historian Chris Baldick, &lt;QUOTE DIRECT=&quot;Y&quot;&gt;Maurice&apos;s own hope was that through the college&apos;s work, &lt;QUOTE DIRECT=&quot;N&quot;&gt;class may be united to class, not by necessity only, but by generous duties and common sympathies.&lt;/QUOTE&gt;&lt;/QUOTE&gt;&lt;BIBCIT&gt;Baldick 63&lt;/BIBCIT&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The direct attribute should only be set to no when you have placed one quote tag inside another. The inner of the two quote tags would be indirect. All other uses of the quote tag should have the direct attribute set to yes.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Each quote should have the direct attribute filled in.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Spacing should read properly when the bibCit is removed.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <attribute name="DIRECT" a:defaultValue="UNSPECIFIED">
                <choice>
                    <value>UNSPECIFIED</value>
                    <value>Y</value>
                    <value>N</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <ref name="corrquoteitem-group"/>
                        <text></text>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="rs-element">
        <element name="RS">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The rs element is a general purpose name element for all names that merit tagging for either display purposes or for search and retrieval, but that are not adequately covered by the name, orgName, place, or title elements.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>rs</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The rs element is a general purpose name element for all names that merit tagging for either display purposes or for search and retrieval, but that are not adequately covered by the name, orgName, place, or title elements.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>rs should be placed around only the word or words that comprise the named object.</xhtml:p>            
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p></xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;rs TYPE=&quot;ship&quot;&gt;Mayflower&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;rs TYPE=&quot;aeroplane&quot;&gt;Concorde&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;rs TYPE=&quot;aeroplane&quot;&gt;Spirit of St Louis&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;rs TYPE=&quot;airship&quot;&gt;Hindenburg&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;rs TYPE=&quot;train&quot;&gt;Orient Express&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;rs TYPE=&quot;automobile&quot;&gt;Edsel&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;rs TYPE=&quot;satellite&quot;&gt;Sputnik 2&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>When using the type attribute in rs, use just the name of the object: i.e. TYPE=&quot;ship&quot; not TYPE=&quot;ship&apos;s name&quot;.</xhtml:p>     
            <xhtml:p>Do not worry about tagging the names of wars, military campaigns, legislation, or any other events that do not need to be set apart typographically.</xhtml:p> 
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag the names of mountains, mountain regions, lakes, rivers, or other geographic features with rs. Instead, consult the documentation on the following sub-elements of place: placeName, region, and geog.</xhtml:p> 
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Question: How do I tag paintings, films, and musical scores? Answer: Use the title element. Treat paintings and films as monographic titles. Songs that are part of a larger collection or CD are treated like poems, using the analytic attribute. If you are naming an entire musical score or spoken word recording or entire album, treat that title as monographic. For further guidelines, see the entry for title in the glossary and consult the MLA handbook.</xhtml:p> 
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="KEY"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="TYPE"/>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="rs-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="corr-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="emph-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="foreign-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="soCalled-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/>-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="docExtent-element">
        <element name="DOCEXTENT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">A carry over from the TEI, docExtent is an element that describes the approximate size of the electronic text as stored on some carrier medium, specified in any convenient units. </a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>docExtent</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>A carry over from the TEI, docExtent is an element that describes the approximate size of the electronic text as stored on some carrier medium, specified in any convenient units. </xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not use this element unless otherwise instructed.</xhtml:p>       
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>docExtent is contained within fileDesc in the OrlandoHeader. It contains no sub-elements, other than the standard linking elements. It has no unique attributes.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                    <text/>
                    <ref name="date-element"/>
                </choice>
            </zeroOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="publicationStmt-element">
        <element name="PUBLICATIONSTMT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">publicationStmt groups information concerning the publication or distribution of an electronic or other text.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>publicationStmt</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>publicationStmt groups information concerning the publication or distribution of an electronic or other text.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;PUBLICATIONSTMT&gt;&lt;AUTHORITY&gt;Orlando Project&lt;/AUTHORITY&gt;&lt;/PUBLICATIONSTMT&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <choice>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <ref name="p-element"/>
                </oneOrMore>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <interleave>
                        <ref name="authority-element"/>
                        <ref name="publicationStmt-group"/>
                    </interleave>
                </oneOrMore>
            </choice>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="authority-element">
        <element name="AUTHORITY">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Part of the the project&apos;s system for cataloguing its own electronic files, the authority element contains the name of the person or organization responsible for the construction of an sgml file. All Orlando documents have the Orlando Project as their authority. Most documents that are assigned already have the information for this element filled in.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>authority</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Part of the the project&apos;s system for cataloguing its own electronic files, the authority element contains the name of the person or organization responsible for the construction of an sgml file. All Orlando documents have the Orlando Project as their authority. Most documents that are assigned already have the information for this element filled in.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Authority is a required element and should contain only the words &quot;Orlando Project.&quot; This element will normally be filled in when you receive your document template.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Authority is available in the publication statement element of the OrlandoHeader and contains only plain text.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;authority&gt;Orlando Project&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p> 
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                    <text/>
                    <ref name="address-element"/>
                    <ref name="date-element"/>
                    <ref name="name-element"/>
                    <ref name="emph-element"/>
                    <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                    <ref name="soCalled-element"/>
                    <ref name="topic-element"/>
                </choice>
            </zeroOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="publicationStmt-group">
        <oneOrMore>
            <group>
                <optional>
                    <ref name="pubPlace-element"/>
                </optional>
                <optional>
                    <ref name="address-element"/>
                </optional>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <ref name="idno-element"/>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <optional>
                    <ref name="availability-element"/>
                </optional>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <ref name="projectDesc-element"/>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <ref name="editorialDecl-element"/>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <optional>
                    <ref name="date-element"/>
                </optional>
            </group>
        </oneOrMore>
    </define>

    <define name="pubPlace-element">
        <element name="PUBPLACE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">pubPlace contains the name of the place where a bibliographic item was published.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>pubPlace</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>pubPlace contains the name of the place where a bibliographic item was published.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="KEY"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                    <text/>
                    <ref name="address-element"/>
                    <ref name="date-element"/>
                    <ref name="name-element"/>
                    <ref name="rs-element"/>
                    <ref name="time-element"/>
                    <ref name="corr-element"/>
                    <ref name="emph-element"/>
                    <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                    <ref name="soCalled-element"/>
                    <ref name="docTitle-element"/>
                    <ref name="topic-element"/>
                </choice>
            </zeroOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="address-element">
        <element name="ADDRESS">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Address, a sub-element within place, captures the specific address where a person lived or where a specific and significant event occurred. Before tagging an address, consider whether it is significant enough to capture in SGML (if a woman writer lived at the address, capture it; if she visited a friend there, probably not). Often for recent writers many addresses are available. Don&apos;t include them all. Include only those significant to the document you are writing.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>address</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Address, a sub-element within place, captures the specific address where a person lived or where a specific and significant event occurred. Before tagging an address, consider whether it is significant enough to capture in SGML (if a woman writer lived at the address, capture it; if she visited a friend there, probably not). Often for recent writers many addresses are available. Don&apos;t include them all. Include only those significant to the document you are writing.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The following types of information can be captured under address:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Private house names (a British phenomenon) and numbered street address (Dunromin or The Nook is part of Address; Sissinghurst Castle is a placeName).</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Street names and squares when they act as addresses and not placenames.</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Lanes, Terraces, Places, Walks</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Parts of streets: i.e., Upper Wimpole Street [Note: provide reg attribute for &quot;Wimpole&quot; in order to ensure the address is indexed in the appropriate place.]</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Address element is placed around one or more addrLine. Addrline is a required sub-element before words are allowed.</xhtml:p>    
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Address is a sub-element within place. It has a required sub-element of addrLine. It has optional attributes for current and reg.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;address&gt;&lt;addrLine&gt;14 Queen&apos;s Row&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;address&gt;&lt;addrLine&gt;George Terrace&lt;/&gt;&lt;addrLine&gt;Commercial Road&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>She lived in &lt;place&gt;&lt;address&gt;King Street&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;in &lt;settlement&gt;London&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;. British practice uses &quot;in&quot; not &quot;on&quot; for streets etc.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>See place for general practice issues.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not abbreviate Street, Avenue, Boulevard, etc. Spell out names in full.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not put a number sign (#) before street numbers in addresses.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>14 Queen&apos;s Row</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Use multiple address lines as you would when addressing an envelope for mailing.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>See placename for distinction between address and placename.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="CURRENT" a:documentation="Current name for geographical location"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <ref name="addrLine-element"/>
                </oneOrMore>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <!-- inclusion for address -->
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="addrLine-element">
        <element name="ADDRLINE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">AddrLine is the required sub-element of address. For definition of an address, see address.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>addrLine</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>AddrLine is the required sub-element of address. For definition of an address, see address.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>One or more addrLine sub-elements can be included in an address tag. Place around the prose specifying the address and exclude punctuation from the tag.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>AddrLine is a required sub-element of address.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>See address for practice issues.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <ref name="name-element"/>
                        <!-- <ref name="rs-element"/> included in addrLine's narrow-inclusion -->
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!-- <ref name="corr-element"/> included in addrLine's narrow-inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="emph-element"/> included in addrLine's narrow-inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="foreign-element"/> included in addrLine's narrow-inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="soCalled-element"/> included in addrLine's narrow-inclusion -->
                        <ref name="topic-element"/>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="name-element">
        <!-- Exclusion: dateStruct, dateRange, 
        keywordClass, name, orgName, place, scholarNote, topic -->
        <element name="NAME">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The name element is used to track people across our history of women&apos;s writing. The contents of the name element will not only be used to index people but to draw attention to the relationships among people, based on the appearance of names in bio-critical documents, in chronology events, and according to proximity searches across the project.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>name</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The name element is used to track people across our history of women&apos;s writing. The contents of the name element will not only be used to index people but to draw attention to the relationships among people, based on the appearance of names in bio-critical documents, in chronology events, and according to proximity searches across the project.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Name should contain only the name of a person and should exclude any extraneous information or punctuation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Name is a global element that can be inserted wherever it is valid to type (i.e. in paragraphs, chronProse, and dataItems). It is modified by the optional standard attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;name&gt;Virginia Woolf&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;name&gt;Sarah Ferguson&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;name&gt;Sarah Flower Adams&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;name STANDARD=&quot;Louis XVI,, King of France&quot;&gt;Louis XVI&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;name STANDARD=&quot;Brougham, Henry Peter,,, Baron&quot;&gt;Lord Brougham&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>In order to systematize names across the project, it is important that a person&apos;s name always be expressed in a standard fashion. To find a person&apos;s standard name please consult the following sources (listed in order of authority). If you cannot find the name in one of these sources or if there is some conflict surrounding the standard name, please contact the appropriate volume author.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>i. Orlando document archive catalog</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>ii. FC: for women writers: (Standard names are written in bold in the FC)</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>iii. Drabble: for male writers</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>iv. DNB: for Brit non-writers (except for those with peerage title)</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>v. BLC online</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>vi. Everyman&apos;s Encyc/Encl Brit</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>vii. LC authority files (author name in the Gate)</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:h3>When and how to standardize a name</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Most names that you enter will not require any use of the standard attribute: names entered in standard format (Lastname, Firstname); names entered in standard reading order provided the ordering of the name is simple first name (can be compound) followed by simple last name (cannot be compound). All other names should be regularized using the tag&apos;s standard attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The use of commas in standard attributes must be precise in order to accommodate complex names. Please use commas carefully and accordingly:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>a single comma would place everything that follows it before everything that precedes it in order to establish natural reading order: Caird, Mona = Mona Caird. Grove, Sir George = Sir George Grove</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>a double comma would place everything that follows it at the end of the name in natural reading order and would add a comma to the display: Marie-Antoinette,, Queen of France = Marie-Antoinette, Queen of France </xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>a triple comma should appear in combination with a single comma and would defer to the ordering principle of the single comma but would add a comma as punctuation: Carlisle, George William Frederick Howard,,, Seventh Earl of = George William Frederick Howard, Seventh Earl of Carlisle</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Difficult names and how to handle them</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>If the name begins with d&apos;, de, von, van and other standard prefixes, and if the person is not indexed in any of the approved list of sources named above, index according to the first capital letter of the surname whether or not it is part of a prefix:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Aelders, Etta Palm d&apos;</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>D&apos;Israeli, Isaac</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Kotezebue, August von</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>La Tourette, Aileen</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>Titles of French people such as comte and marquis should be in lower case:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Artois, comte d&apos;</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Condé, prince de</xhtml:li>     
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>Hyphenate all double-barreled French names:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Marie-Antoinette,, Queen of France</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Voltaire, Jean-Francois-Marie Arouet de</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Due to a software problem, foreign names requiring accents cannot, at this point, acquire accents in the standard attribute. If a name has an accent (such as Madeleine de Scudéry) you will need to put an anglicized version of the name in the standard attribute and then indicate the properly standardized version in a research note placed inside the name tag.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>All references to maiden names, previous names, or future names should not be part of the standard name: such names may appear in the text of the name tag in brackets but should not be part of the standard name unless they are considered a part of the standard name according to the authoritative sources listed above:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Susannah Maria (Arne) Cibber</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Olympe de Gouze (formerly Marie Gouze)</xhtml:li>     
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>Names that have initials should be represented with periods and spaces as follows: in text: T. S. Eliot; in standard attribute: Eliot, T. S.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Where non-peerage titles are part of standard name according to sources above, use abbreviations: Mr, Mrs, Mme, M., Dr, Rev. Note that a period follows the abbreviation only when the abbreviation ends in a letter different from the letter that the word itself ends in.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Monarchs in standard attribute: please note roman numerals and spelling of Tsar.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Of England:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Henry I, King</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Henry IV, King</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Richard II, King</xhtml:li>     
                <xhtml:li>Victoria, Queen</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Elizabeth II, Queen</xhtml:li>  
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>Of other countries:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Alexander II,, Tsar of Russia</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Catherine the Great,, Queen of Russia</xhtml:li>     
                <xhtml:li>Louis IX,, King of France</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Napoleon II,, Emperor of France</xhtml:li>  
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>The standard name of anyone who has been a monarch should be their monarchic name. Therefore, fill in the standard attribute for Prince of Wales and the like to the proper monarchic name. The only exception to this rule is Napoleon Bonaparte whose standard name is not his monarchic name.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Popes and other religious titles in standard attribute: please note roman numerals:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>John XIII, Pope</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Pius IV, Pope</xhtml:li>    
                <xhtml:li>Mary Agnes, Sister</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Hanley, Sister</xhtml:li> 
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>Peerage: all people with peerage titles should be indexed by title (not name) in the standard attribute (the DNB does this the opposite way, so beware). If you have both name and title, use both but remember to index according to title. Occasionally you will find a person who has a peerage title that is not part of a standard name (e.g. Horace Walpole). Defer to the list of sources above in these matters to determine standard name. Spell out all numbers that have to do with peerage titles. Please refer to comma ordering principles listed above.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Montagu, Lady Mary Wortley</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Stanley, Henrietta Maria,,, Lady</xhtml:li>    
                <xhtml:li>North, Lord</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Grove, Sir George</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Northbrook, Thomas George Baring,,, Lord</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Cranworth, Robert Monsey Rolfe,,, Baron</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Condorcet, Marie-Jean-Antoine-Nicolas Caritat,,, marquis de</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>Notes: &quot;Lady&quot; with Christian name means she received her title from her father; "Lady" with surname means she got her title by marriage. &quot;Marquess&quot; is the British spelling for "Marquis"; use for all British people with this title. &quot;Earl&quot;, &quot;Baron&quot;, and &quot;Marquess&quot; are more precise titles than the more general &quot;Lord&quot; which covers the bunch; if you have the more precise title, use it.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>When to tag names and when not to: once per document or chronEvent (look at the editorial guidelines). Also, use the name tag to identify critics, biographers, or historians on whose work you draw.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>For names of ships, trains, and the like, use the rs (referring string) element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h2>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Do I need to standardize names that I type in a possessive form? Answer: You only need to regularize names that appear in a non-standard form inside a name element. When you use a possessive name, simply leave the &apos;s outside the tag to avoid the need to regularize:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;name&gt;Virgina Woolf&lt;/&gt;&apos;s first draft. . .</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Make sure that no extraneous punctuation is included in the name tag because this will interfere with indexing.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: How do I deal with the names of monarchs to ensure they get alphabetized properly? Answer: See examples above.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Should I tag the Dalai Lama or the Archbishop of Canterbury as names? Answer: no.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Can I put more than one name in a name tag? Answer: No.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <ref name="standard-attribute"/>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <text/>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="time-element">
        <element name="TIME">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">time contains a phrase defining a time of day in any format.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>time</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>time contains a phrase defining a time of day in any format.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;TIME&gt;1 a.m.&lt;/TIME&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="VALUE"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="TYPE"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="ZONE"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="certainty-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <text/>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="corr-element">
        <element name="CORR">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Corr, short for correction is an element which contains the correct form of a passage apparently erroneous in your source. This element will be used rarely on Orlando, given that we have checking mechanisms in place for correcting the work of other Orlandians and given that preferred style will be to use the sic element to acknowledge typographical errors in our sources.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>corr</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>corr, short for correction is an element which contains the correct form of a passage apparently erroneous in your source. This element will be used rarely on Orlando, given that we have checking mechanisms in place for correcting the work of other Orlandians and given that preferred style will be to use the sic element to acknowledge typographical errors in our sources.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>corr contains only the corrected portion of an erroneous passage.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>corr contains only text and can be used in paragraph, dataItem, and chronProse elements. corr is modified by the cert and resp attributes.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p></xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Jane Austen&apos;s Love and Freindship &lt;corr&gt;Friendship&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="SIC"/>
            </optional>
            <!-- CDATA -->
            <optional>
                <attribute name="CERT"/>
            </optional>
            <!-- CDATA -->
            <ref name="resp-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <ref name="corrquoteitem-group"/>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="corrquoteitem-group">
        <!-- content used in elements corr, quote, and item -->
        <interleave>
            <group>
                <!-- grouped so interleave does not interfere with choices of either
                l/lg/p followed by 0+ l,lg,p,quote OR 0+ date,name,rs,etc. - test and revise-->
                <choice>
                    <group>
                        <choice>
                            <ref name="l-element"/>
                            <ref name="lg-element"/>
                            <ref name="p-element"/>
                        </choice>
                        <zeroOrMore>
                            <choice>
                                <ref name="l-element"/>
                                <ref name="lg-element"/>
                                <ref name="p-element"/>
                                <ref name="quote-element"/>
                            </choice>
                        </zeroOrMore>
                    </group>
                    <zeroOrMore>
                        <choice>
                            <!--<text/>-->
                            <ref name="date-element"/>
                            <ref name="name-element"/>
                            <ref name="rs-element"/>
                            <ref name="time-element"/>
                            <ref name="corr-element"/>
                            <ref name="emph-element"/>
                            <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                            <ref name="soCalled-element"/>
                            <ref name="quote-element"/>
                            <ref name="topic-element"/>
                            <!-- Div1 inclusion has many overlapping elements, 
                                commenting overlaps would have altered corr and quote's 
                                group choices; non-overlapping elements below-->
                            <ref name="place-element"/>
                            <ref name="orgName-element"/>
                            <ref name="sic-element"/>
                            <ref name="tGenre-element"/>
                            <ref name="xptr-element"/>
                            <ref name="xref-element"/>
                        </choice>
                    </zeroOrMore>
                </choice>
            </group>
            <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
        </interleave>
    </define>

    <define name="idno-element">
        <element name="IDNO">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">idno supplies any form of identifier used to identify some object, such as a bibliographic item, a person, a title, an organization, etc. in a standardized way.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>idno</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>idno supplies any form of identifier used to identify some object, such as a bibliographic item, a person, a title, an organization, etc. in a standardized way.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="TYPE"/>
            </optional>
            <text/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="availability-element">
        <element name="AVAILABILITY">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">This element provides information about the availability of a text, including restrictions on use, distribution, or copyright status. A hold-over from the TEI Header, this element refers to texts that are transcribed as electronic editions and, as such, is not of use in describing Orlando Project documents.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>availability</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>This element provides information about the availability of a text, including restrictions on use, distribution, or copyright status. A hold-over from the TEI Header, this element refers to texts that are transcribed as electronic editions and, as such, is not of use in describing Orlando Project documents.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>            
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>This tag is currently not used by the Orlando Project.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Availability is contained in the OrlandoHeader but is currently not used by the project whatsoever. It has an attribute called status with values of &quot;free&quot; (ie the text is freely available), &quot;unknown,&quot; and &quot;restricted&quot;. </xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="STATUS">
                    <optional>
                        <choice>
                            <value>FREE</value>
                            <value>UNKNOWN</value>
                            <value>RESTRICTED</value>
                        </choice>
                    </optional>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <oneOrMore>
                <ref name="p-element"/>
            </oneOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="projectDesc-element">
        <element name="PROJECTDESC">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">projectDesc describes in detail the aim or purpose for which an electronic file was encoded, together with any other relevant information concerning the process by which it was assembled or collected.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>projectDesc</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>projectDesc describes in detail the aim or purpose for which an electronic file was encoded, together with any other relevant information concerning the process by which it was assembled or collected.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <oneOrMore>
                <ref name="p-element"/>
            </oneOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="editorialDecl-element">
        <element name="EDITORIALDECL">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">editorialDecl provides details of editorial principles and practices applied during the encoding of a text.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>editorialDecl</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>editorialDecl provides details of editorial principles and practices applied during the encoding of a text.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <oneOrMore>
                <ref name="p-element"/>
            </oneOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="sourceDesc-element">
        <element name="SOURCEDESC">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">sourceDesc describes the source from which an electronic text was derived or generated, typically a bibliographic description in the case of a digitized text, or a phrase such as "born digital" for a text which has no previous existence.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>sourceDesc</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>sourceDesc describes the source from which an electronic text was derived or generated, typically a bibliographic description in the case of a digitized text, or a phrase such as "born digital" for a text which has no previous existence.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;SOURCEDESC&gt;Created from original research by members of the Orlando Project&lt;/SOURCEDESC&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <text/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="revisionDesc-element">
        <element name="REVISIONDESC">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">revisionDesc summarizes the revision history for a file.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>revisionDesc</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>revisionDesc summarizes the revision history for a file.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;REVISIONDESC&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="MPO" WORKSTATUS="SUB" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE>5 July 2011&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="IMG" WORKSTATUS="SUB" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;8 September 2011&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="IMG" WORKSTATUS="SUB" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE>8 September 2011&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="IMG" WORKSTATUS="RWT" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;17 February 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="IMG" WORKSTATUS="RWT" WORKVALUE="P"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;20 February 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="NPA" WORKSTATUS="CAS" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE>22 February 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="NPA" WORKSTATUS="CAS" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;23 February 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="NPA" WORKSTATUS="CAS" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;29 February 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="NPA" WORKSTATUS="CAS" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE>1 March 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="IMG" WORKSTATUS="REV" WORKVALUE="C"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;3 March 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY RESP="NPA" WORKSTATUS="CAS" WORKVALUE="C"&gt;&lt;DATE>9 March 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;RESPONSIBILITY WORKSTATUS="CAS" RESP="NPA" WORKVALUE="I"&gt;&lt;DATE&gt;9 March 2012&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;ITEM&gt;&lt;/ITEM&gt;&lt;/RESPONSIBILITY&gt;&lt;/REVISIONDESC&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <oneOrMore>
                <ref name="responsibility-element"/>
            </oneOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="responsibility-element">
        <element name="RESPONSIBILITY">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">resp (or responsibility) contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's intellectual responsibility, or an organization's role in the production or distribution of a work.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>resp</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>resp (or responsibility) contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's intellectual responsibility, or an organization's role in the production or distribution of a work.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <ref name="resp-content"/>
            </optional> 
            <optional>
                <ref name="workStatus-content"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <ref name="workValue-content"/>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <group>
                    <ref name="date-element"/>
                    <zeroOrMore>
                        <ref name="item-element"/>
                    </zeroOrMore>
                </group>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="item-element">
        <element name="ITEM">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">item contains one component of a list.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>item</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>item contains one component of a list.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;ITEM&gt;Initial document given to tagger.&lt;/ITEM&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <ref name="corrquoteitem-group"/>
                        <text></text>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="resp-content">
        <attribute name="RESP" a:defaultValue="IMG">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">resp contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's intellectual responsibility, or an organization's role in the production or distribution of a work.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>resp</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>resp contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's intellectual responsibility, or an organization's role in the production or distribution of a work.</xhtml:p>
            <choice>
                <value type="token">IMG</value>
                <value type="token">SRF</value>
                <value type="token">PDC</value>
                <value type="token">KDC</value>
                <value type="token">ANM</value>
                <value type="token">CNM</value>
                <value type="token">KJB</value>
                <value type="token">TJB</value>
                <value type="token">JAH</value>
                <value type="token">MMM</value>
                <value type="token">SSB</value>
                <value type="token">SIB</value>
                <value type="token">MEL</value>
                <value type="token">JKW</value>
                <value type="token">KKC</value>
                <value type="token">PMB</value>
                <value type="token">TTC</value>
                <value type="token">KAH</value>
                <value type="token">JAW</value>
                <value type="token">SMH</value>
                <value type="token">SYS</value>
                <value type="token">HJM</value>
                <value type="token">CEL</value>
                <value type="token">JSC</value>
                <value type="token">PHD</value>
                <value type="token">AHM</value>
                <value type="token">SJW</value>
                <value type="token">JEB</value>
                <value type="token">SLT</value>
                <value type="token">BAA</value>
                <value type="token">CJH</value>
                <value type="token">JDS</value>
                <value type="token">MEB</value>
                <value type="token">NLG</value>
                <value type="token">CLC</value>
                <value type="token">GCG</value>
                <value type="token">KNT</value>
                <value type="token">JEC</value>
                <value type="token">RSC</value>
                <value type="token">SIR</value>
                <value type="token">ECG</value>
                <value type="token">SLB</value>
                <value type="token">CAG</value>
                <value type="token">MKB</value>
                <value type="token">OSM</value>
                <value type="token">DBH</value>
                <value type="token">KGH</value>
                <value type="token">JJD</value>
                <value type="token">DRG</value>
                <value type="token">NCK</value>
                <value type="token">DLK</value>
                <value type="token">AFP</value>
                <value type="token">KLH</value>
                <value type="token">CEE</value>
                <value type="token">TRN</value>
                <value type="token">RJR</value>
                <value type="token">LMS</value>
                <value type="token">JCA</value>
                <value type="token">JES</value>
                <value type="token">JLT</value>
                <value type="token">KGS</value>
                <value type="token">RJB</value>
                <value type="token">DMH</value>
                <value type="token">MAM</value>
                <value type="token">LKD</value>
                <value type="token">ARP</value>
                <value type="token">KDM</value>
                <value type="token">BJA</value>
                <value type="token">SEV</value>
                <value type="token">AJF</value>
                <value type="token">AGH</value>
                <value type="token">RTM</value>
                <value type="token">LM2</value>
                <value type="token">MRS</value>
                <value type="token">KEH</value>
                <value type="token">CLJ</value>
                <value type="token">JCR</value>
                <value type="token">TCD</value>
                <value type="token">EAQ</value>
                <value type="token">DEK</value>
                <value type="token">BHL</value>
                <value type="token">ALR</value>
                <value type="token">SWK</value>
                <value type="token">JLP</value>
                <value type="token">ACF</value>
                <value type="token">JSE</value>
                <value type="token">MPO</value>
                <value type="token">KCS</value>
                <value type="token">ARC</value>
                <value type="token">AEG</value>
                <value type="token">AVU</value>
                <value type="token">LJH</value>
                <value type="token">KSN</value>
                <value type="token">EWD</value>
                <value type="token">CSK</value>
                <value type="token">JBB</value>
                <value type="token">PAD</value>
                <value type="token">CMD</value>
                <value type="token">CJG</value>
                <value type="token">JRW</value>
                <value type="token">MCA</value>
                <value type="token">AWI</value>
                <value type="token">SKR</value>
                <value type="token">DHA</value>
                <value type="token">SDU</value>
                <value type="token">KGL</value>
                <value type="token">EMH</value>
                <value type="token">AAC</value>
                <value type="token">AJD</value>
                <value type="token">PIH</value>
                <value type="token">GRA</value>
                <value type="token">KFA</value>
                <value type="token">JMA</value>
                <value type="token">CNO</value>
                <value type="token">KSM</value>
                <value type="token">NFS</value><a:documentation>Nora Foster Stovel</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">KME</value><a:documentation>Karyn Huenemann</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">KLM</value><a:documentation>Katie Louise McCullough</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">GLN</value><a:documentation>Graeme Northcote</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">SAH</value><a:documentation>Susan Hesemeier</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">MKD</value><a:documentation>Michelle Di Cintio</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">KMO</value><a:documentation>Kristine Moruzi</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">LSW</value><a:documentation>Larissa Swayze</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">NPA</value><a:documentation>Nadine Adelaar</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">RMB</value><a:documentation>Rebecca Blain</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">JAR</value><a:documentation>Jessica Rattcliffe</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">BJM</value><a:documentation>Breanna Mroczeck</a:documentation>
                <value type="token">DEL</value><a:documentation>Elena Dergacheva</a:documentation>
                
                <!-- Documentation (in progress)
                    <value type="token">ACF</value>
                    <value type="token">JSE</value><a:documentation>Jana Smith Elford</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">MPO</value><a:documentation>Mariana Paredes-Olea</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">KCS</value>
                    <value type="token">ARC</value>
                    <value type="token">AEG</value><a:documentation>Alexandra Guselle</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">AVU</value><a:documentation>Alison Uttley</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">LJH</value><a:documentation>Lisa Hennigar</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">KSN</value><a:documentation>Kayla Snyder</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">EWD</value><a:documentation>Eric Drebit</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">CSK</value><a:documentation>Caley Skinner</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">JBB</value><a:documentation>Justine Baskey</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">PAD</value><a:documentation>Patricia Demers</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">CMD</value><a:documentation>Cecily Devereux</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">CJG</value><a:documentation>Carole Gerson</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">JRW</value><a:documentation>Janice Williamson</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">MCA</value><a:documentation>Marie Carriere</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">AWI</value><a:documentation>Ann Wilson</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">SKR</value><a:documentation>Sidney Kruth</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">DHA</value><a:documentation>Dorothy Hadfield</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">SDU</value><a:documentation>Scott Duchessne</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">PIH</value><a:documentation>Paul Hjartarson</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">GRA</value><a:documentation>GRA training</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">AAC</value><a:documentation>Aldora Cole</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">EMH</value><a:documentation>Emily Hass</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">KGL</value><a:documentation>Kate Lane-Smith</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">NFS</value><a:documentation>Nora Foster Stovel</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">KME</value><a:documentation>Karyn Huenemann</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">MKD</value><a:documentation>Michelle Di Cintio</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">LSW</value><a:documentation>Larissa Swayze</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">NPA</value><a:documentation>Nadine Adelaar</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">RMB</value><a:documentation>Rebecca Blain</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">JAR</value><a:documentation>Jessica Rattcliffe</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">BJM</value><a:documentation>Breanna Mroczeck</a:documentation>
                    <value type="token">DEL</value><a:documentation>Elena Dergacheva</a:documentation> -->
                
            </choice>
        </attribute>
    </define>

    <define name="workStatus-content">
        <attribute name="WORKSTATUS" a:defaultValue="SUB">
            <!-- LS to MP: there's no documentation for this element. -->
            <choice>
                <value type="token">SUB</value>
                <value type="token">RWT</value>
                <value type="token">CAS</value>
                <value type="token">RBV</value>
                <value type="token">CFT</value>
                <value type="token">CFB</value>
                <value type="token">CFC</value>
                <value type="token">REV</value>
                <value type="token">OLD</value>
                <value type="token">PUB</value>
                <value type="token">ENH</value>
            </choice>
        </attribute>
    </define>

    <define name="workValue-content">
        <attribute name="WORKVALUE" a:defaultValue="I">
            <!-- LS to MP: there's no documentation for this element. -->
            <choice>
                <value>I</value>
                <value>P</value>
                <value>C</value>
                <value>O</value>
            </choice>
        </attribute>
    </define>

    <define name="l-element">
        <element name="L">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">l contains a single, possibly incomplete, line of verse.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>l</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>l contains a single, possibly incomplete, line of verse.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;L&gt;All catches alight&lt;/L&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="ENJAMB"/>
            </optional>
            <!--CDATA-->
            <optional>
                <attribute name="MET"/>
            </optional>
            <!--CDATA-->
            <optional>
                <attribute name="REAL"/>
            </optional>
            <!--CDATA-->
            <optional>
                <attribute name="RHYME"/>
            </optional>
            <!--CDATA-->
            <ref name="part-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                        <!--<ref name="rs-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="corr-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                        <!--<ref name="emph-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                        <!--<ref name="foreign-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                        <!--<ref name="soCalled-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                        <!--<ref name="quote-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/> included in Div1-inclusion-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="part-content">
        <attribute name="PART" a:defaultValue="N">
            <!-- LS to MP: there's no documentation for this element. -->
            <choice>
                <value>N</value>
                <value>Y</value>
                <value>I</value>
                <value>M</value>
                <value>F</value>
            </choice>
        </attribute>
    </define>

    <define name="lg-element">
        <element name="LG">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">lg contains a group of verse lines functioning as a formal unit, e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph, etc.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>lg</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>lg contains a group of verse lines functioning as a formal unit, e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph, etc.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;LG TYPE="stanza"&gt;&lt;HEAD&gt;&lt;/HEAD&gt;&lt;L&gt;He loves the haggard frame, the shattered mind,&lt;/L&gt;&amp;amp;lt;L&amp;amp;gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;Gloats with delight upon the glazing eye,&lt;/L&gt;&lt;L&gt;Yet, in one thing His cruelty is kind,&lt;/L&gt;&lt;L&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;He sends them lovely dreams before they die;&lt;/L&gt;&lt;/LG&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <attribute name="TYPE"/>
            <!-- CDATA and check #CURRENT occurrence -->
            <attribute name="ORG" a:defaultValue="UNIFORM">
                <choice>
                    <value>UNIFORM</value>
                    <value>COMPOSITE</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
            <attribute name="SAMPLE" a:defaultValue="COMPLETE">
                <choice>
                    <value>COMPLETE</value>
                    <value>INITIAL</value>
                    <value>MEDIAL</value>
                    <value>FINAL</value>
                    <value>UNKNOWN</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
            <ref name="part-content"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="MET"/>
            </optional>
            <!--CDATA-->
            <optional>
                <attribute name="REAL"/>
            </optional>
            <!--CDATA-->
            <optional>
                <attribute name="RHYME"/>
            </optional>
            <!--CDATA-->
            <interleave>
                <group>
                    <ref name="head-element"/>
                    <oneOrMore>
                        <choice>
                            <ref name="l-element"/>
                            <ref name="lg-element"/>
                        </choice>
                    </oneOrMore>
                </group>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="head-element">
        <element name="HEAD">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">head contains any type of heading, for example the title of a section, or the heading of a list, glossary, manuscript description, etc.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>head</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>head contains any type of heading, for example the title of a section, or the heading of a list, glossary, manuscript description, etc.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="TYPE"/>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!-- <ref name="name-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="rs-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="corr-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="emph-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="foreign-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="soCalled-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="quote-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="topic-element"/> included in Div1 inclusion -->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="p-element">
        <element name="P">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">p marks paragraphs in prose.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>p</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>p marks paragraphs in prose.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;P&gt;Nothing is yet known of her mother.&lt;/P&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <ref name="dateStruct-element"/>
                        <ref name="dateRange-element"/>
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="orgName-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="place-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="emph-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="foreign-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="soCalled-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="quote-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="corr-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="rs-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="title-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="lg-element"/>
                        <ref name="l-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/>-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="dateStruct-element">
        <!-- dateStruct not used anymore by authors, can be removed from 
            schemas after a batch change.-->
        <element name="DATESTRUCT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">DateStruct is one of three elements, along with dateRange and date, used to systematize the capture of dates across project documents. DateStruct is used to tag all singular dates (not ranges) for which individual components (day, month, year) have a varying degrees of certainty or for which only a general season or occasion is known. DateStruct also permits recording the time of day an event occurred.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>dateStruct</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>DateStruct is one of three elements, along with dateRange and date, used to systematize the capture of dates across project documents. DateStruct is used to tag all singular dates (not ranges) for which individual components (day, month, year) have a varying degrees of certainty or for which only a general season or occasion is known. DateStruct also permits recording the time of day an event occurred.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>dateStruct contains only the text that is pertinent to expressing the date at hand and should exclude all unnecessary punctuation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>dateStruct is a global element and should be used only in places where it is possible to type text (paragraphs, chronProse, and dataItems). One of date, dateRange, or dateStruct is required in each chronStruct. dateStruct is modified by the value, calendar, and certainty attributes; every dateStruct no matter how it is typed into your prose must contain a value attribute for the dateStruct as a whole. The sub-elements of dateStruct are day, week, month, year, time, season, and occasion.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateStruct CERTAINTY="C" CALENDAR="NEWSTYLE" VALUE="1868-06-"&gt;&lt;season&gt;Summer&lt;/&gt;&lt;year&gt;1868&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p></xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateStruct CERTAINTY="unknown" CALENDAR="NEWSTYLE" VALUE="1689-10-31"&gt;&lt;day CERTAINTY="unknown"&gt;31&lt;/&gt;&lt;month CERTAINTY="cert"&gt;October&lt;/&gt;&lt;year CERTAINTY="cert"&gt;1689&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="date-attributes"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="year-element"/>
                        <ref name="ocassion-element"/>
                        <ref name="season-element"/>
                        <ref name="month-element"/>
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <ref name="week-element"/>
                        <ref name="day-element"/>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <!-- narrow inclusion: 
                   from Div0 and Div1 except elements in DTD exclusion: 
                   dateStruct , dateRange , keywordClass , name , orgName , 
                   place , date , scholarNote , topic? -->
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="datestruct-content">
        <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="VALUE"/>
        </optional>
        <!-- CDATA in DTD -->
        <optional>
            <attribute name="TYPE"/>
        </optional>
        <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
        <ref name="certainty-content"/>
    </define>

    <define name="year-element">
        <element name="YEAR">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The year element surrounds the name of a year in a dateStruct element. Most years that will be tagged on the project can be included in a simple date element, but those years that have a degree of certainty different from the remainder of the date of which it is part, should be included in a dateStruct--year element.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>year</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The year element surrounds the name of a year in a dateStruct element. Most years that will be tagged on the project can be included in a simple date element, but those years that have a degree of certainty different from the remainder of the date of which it is part, should be included in a dateStruct--year element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Year contains only the text that pertains to the year in question and should, if possible, contain no accompanying text or punctuation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Year is an optional sub-element of dateStruct and is modified by the attributes, value, type, reg, and certainty.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="datestruct-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <text/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="ocassion-element">
        <element name="OCCASION">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The occasion element surrounds dates, such as holidays, that are best referred to by name not date.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>occasion</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The occasion element surrounds dates, such as holidays, that are best referred to by name not date.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Occasion contains only the name of the occasion.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Occasion is an optional sub-element of dateStruct. It has the attributes value, type, reg, and certainty.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>If you use the occasion element, you should always use the value attribute to express the occasion as a numeric date for processing purposes.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="datestruct-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <text/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="season-element">
        <element name="SEASON">
            <!-- LS to MP: there's no documentation for this element. -->
            <ref name="datestruct-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <text/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="month-element">
        <element name="MONTH">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Month is a sub-element of dateStruct and is meant to record only the month portion of a date for which there is a contested or varying degree of certainty among date components.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>month</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Month is a sub-element of dateStruct and is meant to record only the month portion of a date for which there is a contested or varying degree of certainty among date components.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>A sub-element of dateStruct, this element should contain only the month portion of the date that is being recorded.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Month is modified by value, type, certainty and reg attributes.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="datestruct-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <text/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="week-element">
        <element name="WEEK">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The week element surrounds the name of a week in a dateStruct element. Most years that will be tagged on the project can be included in a simple date element, but those years that have a degree of certainty different from the remainder of the date of which it is part, should be included in a dateStruct--year element.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>week</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The week element surrounds the name of a week in a dateStruct element. Most years that will be tagged on the project can be included in a simple date element, but those years that have a degree of certainty different from the remainder of the date of which it is part, should be included in a dateStruct--year element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="datestruct-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <text/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="day-element">
        <element name="DAY">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">A sub-element of dateStruct, day is used to tag the specific day on which an event occurred.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>day</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>A sub-element of dateStruct, day is used to tag the specific day on which an event occurred.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Day should contain only the numeric value of a date. Occasionally, it will contain two or more contested dates, but these dates should be resolved to a single date in the value attribute on dateStruct.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Day is a sub-element of dateStruct and is modified by the value, type, reg, and certainty attributes.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;day&gt;15&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Either the &lt;day VALUE=&quot;23&quot;&gt;21st or 23rd&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="datestruct-content"/>
            <interleave>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                <text/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="dateRange-element">
        <!-- exclusion of dateStruct , 
        dateRange , keywordClass , name , orgName , place , date , 
        scholarNote , topic? -->
        <element name="DATERANGE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Along with date and dateStruct, dateRange is one of three elements used for systematizing dates across the project. Use dateRange for all events that occurred over a span of time or for all dates that are uncertain but that certainly occurred within a specified span of time.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>dateRange</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Along with date and dateStruct, dateRange is one of three elements used for systematizing dates across the project. Use dateRange for all events that occurred over a span of time or for all dates that are uncertain but that certainly occurred within a specified span of time.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>dateRange contains only the text that is pertinent to expressing the range of dates at hand and should exclude all unnecessary punctuation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>dateRange is a global element and should be used only in places where it is possible to type text (paragraphs, chronProse, and dataItems). One of date, dateRange, or dateStruct is required in each chronStruct. dateRange is modified by the calendar, certainty, to, from, and exact attributes. The latter three attributes combine to perform the same function that the value attribute performs in date and dateStruct subelements.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;daterange&gt;1899-March 1902&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The &lt;daterange FROM=&quot;1800&quot; TO=&quot;1899&quot; EXACT=&quot;none&quot;&gt;nineteenth century&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Late in the &lt;dateRange FROM=&quot;1947&quot; TO=&quot;1949&quot; EXACT=&quot;none&apos;&gt;40s&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateRange CERTAINTY=&apos;roughlyDated&quot; FROM=&quot;1847-05-11&quot; TO=&quot;1847-07-30&quot; EXACT=&quot;none&quot;&gt;During the voyage&lt;/&gt; to the colonies, she received word that her novel was accepted for publication.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>When entering dateRanges, follow the standard written format of standardDate1-standardDate2 (12 October 1933-23 October 1933). Such dates do not need to be standardised in the to and from attributes. When tagging a dateRange of years, please make sure you write the years in full. For instance, do not write 1722-25, but 1722-1725. The following date expressions do not need to be regularized in attributes:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateRange&gt;1899-1902&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateRange&gt;14 August 1742-12 March 1745&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateRange&gt;April 1900-June 1900&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateRange&gt;1899-March 1902&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateRange&gt;27 January 1645-March 1656&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dateRange&gt;23 May 1972-1983&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Any dates that are not expressed in this regular fashion will need to have a to, from, and exact attributes filled in.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>When using a broad dateRange in a chronStruct, please consider where you think the event should be sorted for chronology and make note of it in a researchNote inside your dateRange.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Checklist: Make sure that each date you tag conforms to the following practice checklist</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>if you did not need to use a value attribute or if you are just checking the text of the date, check to make sure format is correct: 7 January 1898 (the date can be truncated from the left but not from the right). Are they any typos? Remove leading 0 in single digit text dates.</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>if you are checking the value attribute, make sure format is correct: 1983-01-10, 1983-01-, 1983--. Make sure leading 0 is present for single digit months and days. Make sure both hyphens are present. Add text to tag if it is missing (especially in chronStruct)</xhtml:li>     
                <xhtml:li>where necessary, move spaces/punctuation (or add spaces) outside tag to ensure doc reads properly</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>remove any bibCits in the tag and place them in the appropriate place</xhtml:li> 
                <xhtml:li>remove any research notes from inside the tag and place them just outside the end tag (or delete it they are trivial and the problem has been fixed)</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>remove any empty date tags except in files that are template only--fix doc where necessary if this makes the doc invalid</xhtml:li> 
            </xhtml:ul>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <ref name="calendar-content"/>
            <ref name="certainty-content"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="FROM"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="TO"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="EXACT">
                    <choice>
                        <value>TO</value>
                        <value>FROM</value>
                        <value>BOTH</value>
                        <value>NEITHER</value>
                    </choice>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <text/>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="orgName-element">
        <element name="ORGNAME">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The orgName element is used to identify schools, companies, and any other type of recognized organization.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>orgName</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The orgName element is used to identify schools, companies, and any other type of recognized organization.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>orgName contains only the name of the organization with no surrounding text or punctuation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>orgName is available wherever it is valid to type in a document (i.e. paragraphs, chronProse, and dataItems). It is modified by the attributes reg, standard, and orgType. Reg is used to indicate the regularized form of the organization nate at the time contemporary to the reference; Standard is used to indicate the standard non-historically specific organization name.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>If the leading article is part of the orgName (the, a, an) include it in the tag. If it is not part of the orgName, place it outside the tag.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>It is project practice to place a comma before the &quot;and&quot; when listing items in a series. However, when writing an orgName, use the format as it appears in the original source: don&apos;t change the comma to conform to project practice. If the same organization is referred to multiple ways in our documents (with respect to commas) opt for the majority or defer to the project practice.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Names that have initials should be represented with periods and spaces as follows: A. K. Newman. Do not reverse order such names in standard attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you need to tag a name that is part of the orgName, you can use an empty tag regularised to the proper name; insert the empty element directly after the orgName to which it refers. In general, the reg attribute allows you to insert the proper name of an organization when it has not otherwise been possible. For example, all adjectival forms of organizations should be standardised as proper nouns. This means that all instances of &quot;Anglican&quot; would be standardised as Anglican Church. Catholic or Roman Catholicism would be standardised as Roman Catholic Church.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The REG attribute on OrgName is used to indicate the regularized form of the organization name at the time contemporary with the reference to it; STANDARD is used to indicate the standard or non-historically specific organization name. If a value for one or both of these attributes is not specified, then the system takes what is given in the text of the tag as the default value(s).</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>orgNames vary over time. Use the reg attribute the indicate the name of the organization contemporary to the reference of it in the Orlando document. The "standard" attribute allows you to standardize an organization&apos;s name to its current coinage. In many cases the two names will be the same. If they are the same and the text of the tag contains this standard orgName, then you will not need to fill in any attributes.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If an orgName is standardly and commonly known as an abbreviation, use the abbreviation as the standard and use the full form of the name as in the reg attribute:&lt;orgName standard = BBC reg = British Broadcasting Corporation&gt;BBC&lt;/orgName&gt; or &lt;orgName standard = PEN reg = Society of Poets, Essayists, and Novelists&gt;PEN&lt;/orgName&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The use of commas in the standard attribute must be precise to accommodate complex orgNames. A single comma would place everything that follows it before everything that precedes it in order to establish a natural reading order: Friends, Society of = Society of Friends. A double comma would place everything that follows it at the end of the orgName in natural reading order and would add a comma to the display. Burns,, Lambert and Oates = Burns, Lambert and Oates. If you encounter orgNames more complex than can be accommodated by single and double commas, please consult the triple comma rule under name.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Please note: these rules for using commas apply only in the standard and reg attributes. If you enter an orgName in the text of your tag in a standard fashion, then you will not need to worry about these rules.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>To check the standard form of an orgName, check <em>Whitaker&apos;s Almanack</em> or <em>The London Encyclopedia</em>. Sally Mitchell&apos;s <em>Victorian Britain</em> and the <em>New Cambridge Companion to Victorian Literature and Culture</em> are good sources for the nineteenth- century period.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>When a geographical place is not part of the standard name of an organization , do not include it in the standard attribute as a referent but do use a place tag (silent or not) following the orgName tag. You do not need to add a place tag if the place has been tagged elsewhere in a chronEvent or a shortProse. An exception to this rule: include place in the standard attribute of an orgName only when two or more places of identical name but different jurisdiction exist in the system: University College,, Sheffield; University College,, Dundee; University College,,Cardiff.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Research notes should not appear inside an orgName tag. If an orgName has an accented character and must be standardised in the standard attribute, please put an anglicized version of the name in the standard attribute and place a research note just inside the &lt;name&gt; tag that reads &lt;researchNote&gt; standard: orgName&lt;/researchNote&gt; where orgName represents the properly standardised version of the orgName including all accents/entity references.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Colleges and Universities</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Do not reverse the order of &quot;University of xxx&quot; in the standard attribute. Correct: University of Leeds.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Use Oxford University and Cambridge University as the standard name for those institutions. For all others (except the University of Manchester) consult <em>Whitaker&apos;s Almanack</em>. The University of Manchester and Owens College are different/historically specific ways of referring to Victoria University of Manchester. Please standardise all instances to the latter, so that the proper rendering is as follows:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;orgName standard = Victoria University of Manchester&gt;&lt;/orgName&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>For all colleges of Oxford University, Cambridge University and the University of London, please make sure standard attribute is filled in to refer to both college and larger university. You can find a list of all the colleges of these institutions in <em>Whitaker&apos;s Almanack</em>.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;orgName standard = St Hilda&apos;s College,,Oxford University&gt;St Hilda&apos;s College&lt;/orgName&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Theatres</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The theatres in Covent Garden, Drury Lane, and Haymarket should all be standardised as royal charter theatres as follows:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;orgName standard = Theatre Royal, Covent Garden&gt;Covent Garden&lt;/orgname&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;orgName standard = Theatre Royal, Drury Lane&gt;Drury Lane&lt;/orgname&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;orgName standard = Theatre Royal, Haymarket&gt;Haymarket&lt;/orgname&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Churches</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Standardise all instances of Anglican, Church of England, Church of Ireland, Church of India, Church of South India, and Episcopalian, to Anglican Church.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>All references to Methodist Church, Wesleyan Methodist Church, Primitive Methodist Church, United Methodist Church, Methodist New Connexion, Bible Christian Methodist Church and United Methodist Free Churches should be standardized to Methodist Church (&lt;ORGNAME STANDARD=&quot;Methodist Church&quot;&gt;)</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Governments and Parliaments</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>For British Parliament, use only &quot;parliament&quot; with capital "P"; standardised as such only if prose demands lowercase &quot;p&quot;. Standardise all instances of British government to &apos;parliament&quot; as well but use the more specific House of Commons and House of Lords where applicable.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>For other governments and parliaments, use adjectival form for jurisdiction before the word Parliament (or equivalent): Russian Parliament, Irish Parliament, United States Congress. Do not standardise as Parliament, Russian.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>For the Tory Party vs Conservative Party and Whig Party vs Liberal Party, do the following: Pre 1830: &lt;orgName standard = Coservative Party reg = Tory Party&gt;. This means that today&apos;s standard is Conservative Party but it was then regularly known as the Tory Party. After 1830, the standard attribute should read &quot;Conservative Party&quot; and the reg attribute should read &quot;Conservative.&quot; Before June 1859, standard = Liberal Party and reg = Whig Party. This means that today&apos;s standard is Liberal Party but it was then standardly known as the Whig Party. After June 1859 standard = Liberal Party, and the reg = Liberal.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Publishers</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>For publishers whose name is also a person&apos;s name, standardise and reg as the name in the natural reading order. &lt;orgName&gt;Jonathan Cape&lt;/orgName&gt; or &lt;orgName standard = Jonathan Cape reg = Jonathan Cape&gt;Cape&lt;/orgName&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>To check the proper name of a publisher, first check to see if there is an event on the founding of the company; if the event has been source checked, please standardise according to how the orgName appears in that event.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Should I tag journal titles as orgNames? Answer: No.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Can I use an orgName tag to cover more than one orgName? Answer: No, they must be tagged separately.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <ref name="standard-attribute"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="ORGTYPE"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
            <mixed>
                <!-- changed interleave to mixed, and deleted <text> -->
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
            </mixed>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="place-element">
        <!-- has exclusion -->
        <element name="PLACE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Place is a universal element, available throughout most Orlando Project SGML elements, which structures information about geographical location. Locating events and people is a priority of our Project. By emphasizing the facts of where events occurred, we will be able to bring together people and places, uncovering geographical connections between writers as yet undiscovered. <br/>There are two main goals for tagging place: mapping and indexing. We hope to automatically provide our end users with maps of literary history. For example, by using the places tagged with biography documents, we hope to generate a map for each woman writer&apos;s life which places her in specific places at specific times in her life. We also hope to allow end users to see a map of events for a particular year which would bring together geographical information from all Project DTDs. In order to automate mapping, it is crucial that we provide place information in a structured and recognizable way. In addition to mapping, we want to provide end users with an index of places. For example, we want to be able to index all women writers who lived in Bloomsbury or all events which took place in Bath. <br/>While we prioritize the tagging of place, not all places require tagging. We hope to enhance our geographical information by context specific tagging. For example, by tagging only places where events occurred inside Event DTD chronstructs and not all places mentioned within the prose, we will be able to map that event to the place tagged. See Practice Issues below for a discussion of context specific practices.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>place</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Place is a universal element, available throughout most Orlando Project SGML elements, which structures information about geographical location. Locating events and people is a priority of our Project. By emphasizing the facts of where events occurred, we will be able to bring together people and places, uncovering geographical connections between writers as yet undiscovered.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>There are two main goals for tagging place: mapping and indexing. We hope to automatically provide our end users with maps of literary history. For example, by using the places tagged with biography documents, we hope to generate a map for each woman writer&apos;s life which places her in specific places at specific times in her life. We also hope to allow end users to see a map of events for a particular year which would bring together geographical information from all Project DTDs. In order to automate mapping, it is crucial that we provide place information in a structured and recognizable way. In addition to mapping, we want to provide end users with an index of places. For example, we want to be able to index all women writers who lived in Bloomsbury or all events which took place in Bath.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>While we prioritize the tagging of place, not all places require tagging. We hope to enhance our geographical information by context specific tagging. For example, by tagging only places where events occurred inside Event DTD chronstructs and not all places mentioned within the prose, we will be able to map that event to the place tagged. See Practice Issues below for a discussion of context specific practices.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Place is the largest bucket holding together the sub-elements dividing place into country, city, town, etc. All content information --- i.e., the names of places -- should be placed inside its sub-elements. Place does allow free prose which can be used to leave unimportant locations untagged and to enter punctuation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Place is a universal element available in all DTDs and within most elements. Place has the following content sub-elements which divide place into smaller units: placename, address, settlement, region, and geog.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;&lt;settlement&gt;Tokyo&lt;/&gt;,&lt;geog&gt;Japan&lt;/&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;&lt;settlement&gt;Hanworth&lt;/&gt;,&lt;region&gt;Middlesex&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>She died at &lt;place&gt;&lt;address&gt;&lt;addrLine&gt;George Street&lt;/&gt;, &lt;addrLine&gt;hanover Square&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;, &lt;settlement&gt;London&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Sources: For problem places check Atlases available in your Project reference section. Webster&apos;s Dictionary provides a lengthy appendix on Geographical Places which gives useful information and proper spelling. For help with determining which region within the British Isles your settlement is in, the on-line Ordinance Survey is a quick tool. [http://www.campus.bt.com/CampusWorld/pub/OS/Gazetteer/index.html]</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Place all punctuation and spaces outside place sub-elements.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;&lt;settlement&gt;Casablanca&lt;/&gt;, &lt;geog&gt;Morocco&lt;/&gt;.&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Put the apostrophe and &quot;s&quot; in possessive words outside the sub-element. For example, do not include &apos;Italy&apos;s&quot; within a geog tag but place tag only around &quot;Italy&quot;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;&lt;geog&gt;Italy&lt;/&gt;&apos;s&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>During &lt;place&gt;&lt;geog&gt;Canada&lt;/&gt;&apos;s&lt;/&gt; separation debates, she travelled through the country.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not include articles (the, a) within the place sub-element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;The &lt;region&gt;Lake District&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag all places. Use you best judgement on determining relevant places but as a general rule, only tag places that are significant to a person&apos;s life and writing or an historical event. For example, if a woman writer lived in the village of Little Wittering, while the place is obscure, tag it as tagging it may allow us to discover that another woman writer lived or wrote there in a different century. But if the writer split up with a lover who then went off to live in Little Wittering, or if she applied for a job there but didn&apos;t get it, do not tag it.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag places within biography and writing documents that refer to general world events rather than the particular people when these events will be entered elsewhere. In the example below, tag Florence because Radclyffe Hall was in Florence during that time but do not tag the reference to Italy in the shortprose because WWII will be covered in an Events document.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;chronStruct&gt;&lt;dateRange&gt;6 November 1921-7 January 1922&lt;/&gt;&lt;chronProse&gt; RH and Una visited &lt;place&gt;&lt;settlement&gt;Florence&lt;/&gt;&lt;geog REG=&quot;Italy&quot;&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;, staying at the Hotel Albion.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;shortprose&gt;&lt;p&gt; The sided with the Fascists in the midst of Italy&apos;s political upheaval.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not tag the same place twice in one document unless it refers to two logically separate places. If she lived in London and you have tagged her move to London, all subsequent life events which take place in London do not require place tags. However, if she then moved to Bath and returned to London, tag the return to London.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>All places must have a recognizable location tagged. In order to automate mapping, the computer will search from smallest to largest conceptual location (i.e., settlement to region to geog) and map the place according to the smallest recognizable place. Therefore, if the smaller conceptual name is not recognizable you must add a larger sub-element, even if it means using a place sub-element with only the reg attribute filled in (see below). If you do not know whether a place is recognizable and identifiable by itself, check with your supervisor. In the example below, do NOT simply tag British Museum. You must include the empty settlement tag for mapping purposes.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>She had the idea for her novel standing on the steps of the &lt;place&gt;&lt;placeName&gt;British Museum&lt;/&gt;&lt;settlement REG=&apos;London&quot;&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>You must include a region sub-element for all places in the British Isles. See region glossary entry for a list of regions to use and a list of exceptions to this rule.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>You must include a geog sub-element for all places outside the British Isles. See geog glossary entry for a list of exceptions to this rule.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you do not want to enter necessary place information in the prose of your sentence, use the appropriate place sub-element and provide the information only in the reg attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>While in &lt;place&gt;&lt;settlement&gt;Casablanca&lt;/&gt;&lt;geog REG=&quot;Morocco&quot;&gt;&lt;/&gt;, she met her future husband.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>You can refer to a place in the prose using whatever word you want, but you must regularize a place referred to in a non-standard way. A common example of this occurs when adjectives are used instead of proper names and the proper name is given inside a reg attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>She met Eleanor Roosevelt during her &lt;place&gt;&lt;geog REG=&quot;USA&quot;&gt;American&lt;/&gt; lecture tour.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>You can use two of the same place sub-elements within one place element in capturing information concerning a logically singular place. For example, if you wish to capture that she lived in the Rocky Mountains in Alberta, since both Rocky Mountains and Alberta are regions, capture them in two region sub-elements. You can only do this when the place is logically one place (i.e., a settlement within a settlement) and not for references to logically different settlements (i.e., &quot;She travelled from London to Paris&quot; requires two place elements).</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If a place has a specific directional marker (i.e., eastern, western, northern, southern), include that marker in the prose but regularize without the direction.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;&lt;geog REG=&quot;France&quot;&gt;southern France&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;&lt;geog REG=&quot;Asia&quot;&gt;Central Asia&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;place&gt;&lt;settlement REG=&quot;London&quot;&gt;East London&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>When a place sub-element is a given a reg or current attribute, the content of these attributes will take priority over the content of the element&apos;s prose for mapping and indexing.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>All places tagged within a Div1 Location element within Biography will be assumed to refer to the place where the person was and will be mapped accordingly.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Only tag place in a chronstruct inside an Events document if it is the place where the chronology event occurred.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Only tag place in a chronstruct inside a Biography and Writing document if it can be used to map where the subject of the documents was on the date specified. Do not tag if the place in the chronology event refers to where someone else was (for example, &quot;Her brother died in London&quot;). If an end user wants to see a map of George Eliot&apos;s life, all places tagged within chronstructs will be assumed to place where Eliot was on a certain date and be mapped accordingly. In the below example, the map will locate Eliot in Florence in 1860.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;chronStruct&gt;&lt;date&gt;1860&lt;/&gt;&lt;chronProse&gt;George Eliot visited &lt;place&gt;&lt;settlement&gt;Florence&lt;/&gt;&lt;geog REG=&quot;Italy&quot;&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;.&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p></xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>In order to determine whether or not a place should be captured inside a place element, ask yourself the following questions:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>If I am inside a chronstruct in an Events document, is the place I want to tag the place where the chronology event occurred?</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>If I am inside a chronstruct in a Biography or Writing document, does the place I want to tag refer to where the subject was on that date?</xhtml:li>     
                <xhtml:li>Is this place likely to come up again Orlando&apos;s literary history? Or is it an obscure place that would not be useful to point out end users toward?</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:p>Question: When can I use two of the same element within one place tag?</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Answer: You can only use two of the same element when the place captured within the tag is one logical place and requires to settlement tags to clearly define it. For example, &quot;She travelled from London to Paris&quot; requires two separate place elements and not just two settlement tags within one place.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <element name="PLACENAME">
                            <ref name="placeChild-content"/>
                        </element>
                        <ref name="address-element"/>
                        <element name="SETTLEMENT">
                            <ref name="placeChild-content"/>
                        </element>
                        <element name="REGION">
                            <ref name="placeChild-content"/>
                        </element>
                        <element name="GEOG">
                            <ref name="placeChild-content"/>
                        </element>
                        <element name="AREA">
                            <ref name="placeChild-content"/>
                        </element>
                        <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="placeChild-content">
        <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="CURRENT"/>
        </optional>
        <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
        <interleave>
            <text/>
            <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
        </interleave>
    </define>

    <define name="title-element">
        <element name="TITLE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The title element contains the title of a work, whether article, book, journal (newspaper, magazine), series, or unpublished.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>title</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The title element contains the title of a work, whether article, book, journal (newspaper, magazine), series, or unpublished.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The title element should be placed around only those words which are part of the title and which should be set apart typographically. Do not include any punctuation in the title tag that is not part of the title itself.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Title is available from the Div1 level on down and should be used only in those places where typing is allowed (ie headings, chronProse, dataItems, and shortProse). Its only attribute, titleType, indicates whether the work is an article, book, journal, series, or unpublished material.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;monographic&quot;&gt;The Martyr, A Drama&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;monographic&quot;&gt;Sense and Sensibility&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;analytic&quot;&gt;Sonnet CXVI&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;analytic&quot;&gt;Metaphor of Metonymy? The Question of Essentialism in Cixous&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;journal&quot;&gt;English Studies in Canada&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;journal&quot;&gt;The New York Times&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;series&quot;&gt;Mothers of the Novel&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;series&quot;&gt;Contemporary Authors&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;unpublished&quot;&gt;Elinor and Marianne&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;unpublished&quot;&gt;Lady Susan&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>If you are writing about an author&apos;s work before it became a published text, you may use the attribute that is appropriate for the title at that point in its evolution. This means that you can use the attribute "unpublished" if you are writing about a manuscript version of a book that was later published. Of course, you would only choose to do this in a situation where there&apos;s something substantive to be said about the work in its unpublished state.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>A title must be tagged with its titleType attribute filled in every time it appears in your prose. If it is not, it will not be displayed properly in the final product. However, do not tag titles in a bibCit, but do tag them in worksCited.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>When tagging a series title in your prose, do not include the series number as part of the title.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>You will be able to use a volumeIdentification tag for the series number in your bibliogrpahic citation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Gift books and annuals should be treated as series.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Treat the paintings, films, and musical scores as titles. Paintings and films are monographic titles. Songs that are part of a larger collection or CD are treated like poems, using the analytic attribute. If you are naming an entire musical score or spoken word recording or entire album, treat that title as monographic. For further guidelines consult the MLA handbook.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Vanessa Bell and Duncan Grant painted &lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;monographic&quot;&gt;dining room with panels&lt;/&gt; at Penn-in-the-Rocks, Wythitham, Sussex.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Leslie Howard starred in two British films, &lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;monographic&quot;&gt;The First of the Few&lt;/&gt; and &lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;monographic&quot;&gt;49th Parallel&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Ethel Smyth&apos;s opera &lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;monographic&quot;&gt;The Boatswain&apos;s Mate&lt;/&gt; was played at Shaftesbury Theatre in London.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Florrie Ford, a music-hall artist endorsed the song &lt;title TITLETYPE=&quot;analytic&quot;&gt;It&apos;s a long way to Tipperary&lt;/&gt;, making it popular.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>RELATION TO THE BIBLIOGRAPHY DATABASE: Every title in the bio and writing docs has a biblio entry to which it should be linked, so unless the title and biblio entry are exactly the same, the reg attribute must link the title to the database entry. To make the title agree, it must be EXACTLY the same in every respect (capitalisation, punctuation, spacing etc) as the title in the Monographic Std Title box in the bibliographic database. If this is not possible, then the Reg attribute must agree with the Monographic Alt Title ot the Imprint Title Pape Title in the biblio entry.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Question: My title begins with the word &quot;the&quot;: should I place &quot;the&quot; in the title tag? Answer: If &quot;the&quot; is part of the title, it should be included in the title tag. Sometimes, it is not easy to determine whether the &quot;the&quot; is in fact part of the title. You can find out this information, by checking the title page or the masthead of newspapers or by consulting the library&apos;s catalogue record.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Do I include the &quot;The&quot; when referring to The Times (of London) and how do I distinguish it from the New York Times? Answer: For our project, we&apos;ll assume that &quot;The Times&quot; refers to the London Times, but you must tag the masthead title of &quot;New York Times&quot; or &quot;Los Angeles Times&quot; when discussing those papers.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: How do I tag government documents? Answer: Most government publications are authored and published by the government that produces them. Most government titles should be tagged as monographic. For more information on the proper method to cite government documents, please consult the MLA handbook.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: What attribute is the right one when tagging a government document? Answer: If the document is unpublished, use unpublished. If published, use monographic.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Do I tag a title if it appears in a bitCit? Answer: No.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Do I tag a title in a WorksCited List? Answer: No.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: I am writing about the manuscript version of a book that was later published. Should I use the attribute for monographic or unpublished? Answer: you can use whichever attribute is appropriate to the context in which you are discussing the book: unpublished before its publication and monographic after its publication.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Question: I want to tag a book of the Bible. How do I do it? The Bible is tagged as monographic. In the attributes, in the &quot;rend&quot; field, type normal. The books of the Bible (Genesis, etc) are analytic, but the &quot;rend&quot; attribute should also read &quot;normal&quot;.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="TITLETYPE">
                    <choice>
                        <value>MONOGRAPHIC</value>
                        <value>ANALYTIC</value>
                        <value>JOURNAL</value>
                        <value>SERIES</value>
                        <value>UNPUBLISHED</value>
                    </choice>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="REND"/>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <!--<ref name="title-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="emph-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="foreign-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="soCalled-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="quote-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/>-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="topic-element">
        <element name="TOPIC">
            <!-- exclusion of dateStruct , dateRange , 
            keywordClass , name , topic , orgName , place , scholarNote -->
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">This element applies to both theme and topic. Theme is the central idea in a text stated either directly or indirectly; topic applies to interesting subjects appearing in a work that might not aspire to the status of a "theme" and is useful in genres such as educational or non-fictional texts.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>themeTopic</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>This element applies to both theme and topic. Theme is the central idea in a text stated either directly or indirectly; topic applies to interesting subjects appearing in a work that might not aspire to the status of a "theme" and is useful in genres such as educational or non-fictional texts.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Occurring in the TextualFeatures component, this element should be used around one or two descriptive words. You should also use it around a name if a person was the topic of a book or article, for example. So if a woman writer wrote a book on Sappho, use both the name tag and the themeTopic tag around the name of Sappho.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>There are no mandatory or optional sub-elements or attributes for this element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;tThemeTopic&gt; forced marriage&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;tThemeTopic&gt; Oriental, African, pastoral, medieval, and contemporary subjects&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;tThemeTopic&gt; Colonial oppression&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Theme differs from motif in that theme is larger scale, appears throughout the work and differs from sub-genre in that theme is not a work's defining principle.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Topic can be used if a woman wrote a cookbook, a non-fiction work on stitchery, or an educational text which used the Napoleanic wars for examples. None of these subjects could be properly described as themes; they are topics.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <ref name="standard-attribute"/>
            </optional>
            <!-- CDATA -->
            <interleave>
                <text/>
                <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <!-- Div0 starts -->

    <define name="Div0-element">
        <!-- this Div0 is used in events only -->
        <element name="DIV0">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Div0 (i.e. level-0 text division) is the largest structural element permitted in any Orlando document. SGML works on the principle that all information in a document exists hierarchically, or, stated otherwise, that all types of information can be contained in other types of information. For the Orlando Project, Div0 is the element that contains everything in a document except the cataloguing information that is contained in the Orlando Header.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>Div0</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Div0 (i.e. level-0 text division) is the largest structural element permitted in any Orlando document. SGML works on the principle that all information in a document exists hierarchically, or, stated otherwise, that all types of information can be contained in other types of information. For the Orlando Project, Div0 is the element that contains everything in a document except the cataloguing information that is contained in the Orlando Header.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Div0 is a required element immediately following the OrlandoHeader in biography, events, and writing documents. All other elements (excluding those found in the OrlandoHeader) are contained within a Div0.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;Events&gt;&lt;OrlandoHeader&gt;>. . . All project cataloguing information is tagged here. . . &lt;/&gt;&lt;Div0&gt;All subsequent document sub-divisions occur here. . . &lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <group>
                    <optional>
                        <ref name="heading-element"/>
                    </optional>
                    <zeroOrMore>
                        <ref name="Div1-element"/>
                    </zeroOrMore>
                </group>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="Div1-element">
        <element name="DIV1">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Div1 (i.e. level-1 text division) is an element that marks the second largest structural division in a document.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>Div1</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Div1 (i.e. level-1 text division) is an element that marks the second largest structural division in a document.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>In Events documents, Div1 is contained inside a Div0, following the optional Div0--heading; here it contains an optional heading, one or more chronEvents, and a worksCited. In Biography documents, Div1 follows heading and standard (name) elements inside a Div0. It contains one of a number of anchored content tags, such as birth, death, and education. In Writing documents, a Div1 occurs following a Div0--heading and contains an optional heading followed by a Div2 with a corresponding textScope.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;Div0&gt;&lt;heading&gt;Biography&lt;/&gt;&lt;standard&gt;Abdy, Maria&lt;/&gt;&lt;Div1&gt;All subsequent document sub-divisions occur here. . .&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <group>
                        <choice>
                            <optional>
                                <ref name="heading-element"/>
                            </optional>
                            <zeroOrMore>
                                <ref name="chronEvent-element"/>
                            </zeroOrMore>
                            <zeroOrMore>
                                <ref name="worksCited-element"/>
                            </zeroOrMore>
                        </choice>
                    </group>
                </oneOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="heading-element">
        <!-- exclusion: datestruct, daterange, date,
        keywordclass, name, orgname, place, topic , bibcit (bio DTD)-->
        <element name="HEADING">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">head (or heading) contains any type of heading, for example the title of a section, or the heading of a list, glossary, manuscript description, etc.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>head</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>head (or heading) contains any type of heading, for example the title of a section, or the heading of a list, glossary, manuscript description, etc.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                    <text/>
                    <ref name="narrow-inclusion"/>
                </choice>
            </zeroOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="chronEvent-element">
        <element name="CHRONEVENT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">ChronEvent is an element that holds together all relevant information pertaining to an individual chronology entry as well as its explanatory material.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>chronEvent</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>ChronEvent is an element that holds together all relevant information pertaining to an individual chronology entry as well as its explanatory material.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>An events document is a collection of multiple chronEvents, which will be processed eventually into individual files. Writing and Biography documents do not contain a chronEvent element--in these documents it is sufficient to use a chronStruct element followed, if necessary, by a shortProse element to contextualize chronology material.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>chronEvent is contained by Div1 and contains one and only one chronstruct element. It also includes a responsibility element with the possibility for optional shortProse, extendedProse, and dataStruct elements. Each chronEvent should have at least one bibCit associated with it.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;chronEvent&gt;&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;writingClimate&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1960&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;The trial by jury of Penguin Books regarding the publication of Lady Chatterly&apos;s Lover by D.H. Lawrence began at the Old Bailey.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;ShortProse&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those called in as expert witnesses included E.M. Forster, Helen Gardner, C. Day Lewis, Dilys Powell, Professor Vivian de Sola Pinto, Janet Adam Smith, Sir Stanley Unwin, and Dame Rebecca West. &lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;responsibility RESP=&quot;KAH&quot; RESPCATEGORY=&quot;researched&quot; STATUS=&quot;incomplete&quot;&gt;&lt;date&gt;11 March 1997&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;bibCit&gt;Craig 163&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;chronEvent&gt;&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;nationalInternational&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1911&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Local authorities (Ireland) Qualification of Women Act gave women the right to become councillors or aldermen on county councils.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;ShortProse&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women in England, Wales and Scotland had received this same right in 1907. &lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;responsibility RESP=&quot;MMM&quot; RESPCATEGORY=&quot;researched&quot; STATUS=&quot;incomplete&quot;&gt;&lt;date&gt;18 March 1997&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;bibCit&gt;Harvey 519&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>An individual chronEvent will eventually be separated from the surrounding events with which it was created. Individual events may appear in the over-arching project chronology or within subject specific chronologies. Because of the multiple contexts which could come to bear on a chronEvent, it is vital that each event be a conceptually independent. Please make sure that all pronouns used in a chronEvent have their referent in the chronProse of that event. Also make sure that all names, dates, places, and orgNames are tagged once per chronEvent.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <group>
                    <ref name="chronStruct-element"/>
                    <oneOrMore>
                        <choice>
                            <ref name="dataStruct-element"/>
                            <ref name="shortProse-element"/>
                            <zeroOrMore>
                                <ref name="responsibility-element"/>
                            </zeroOrMore>
                        </choice>
                    </oneOrMore>
                </group>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="chronColumn-attributes">
        <optional>
            <attribute name="CHRONCOLUMN">
                <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">ChronColumn is an attribute which designates a given chronology item as belonging to a subject-specific column of the Orlando print (and possibly electronic) chronology.</a:documentation>
                <xhtml:h2>chronColumn</xhtml:h2>            
                <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>ChronColumn is an attribute which designates a given chronology item as belonging to a subject-specific column of the Orlando print (and possibly electronic) chronology.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>ChronColumn is a mandatory attribute of chronStruct and has four values: &quot;nationalInternational,&quot; &quot;BritishWomenWriters,&quot; &quot;writingClimate,&quot; and &quot;socialClimate.&quot; These attribute values carry the following connotations: &quot;National/International Events&quot;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:ul>
                    <xhtml:li>British-centric events with major implications in Europe, colonies, or world-wide;</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>major foreign events which affected Britain either politically or socially (eg., Russian Revolution);</xhtml:li>  
                    <xhtml:li>establishment of major national and international organizations (eg., League of Nations, Oxfam, International Labour Organization);</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>change in status of countries&apos; governing structure, especially colonies, former colonies, and close allies (eg. independence, coups);</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>British monarchs accession;</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>British national elections;</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>major British military engagements (eg., Boer War, major campaigns of WWI &#38; II, in India)</xhtml:li>
                </xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:p>&quot;Social Climate&quot; The items in this column will frequently refer not to discrete events but to larger trends or practices affecting women; this means that dates may often be approximate. (note: please always regularise approximate or uncertain dates in the value attribute of date)The following are types of information appropriate to this column:</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:ul>
                    <xhtml:li>advances, developments, or regressions in the areas of technology, science, medicine, law</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>education</xhtml:li>     
                    <xhtml:li>conditions surrounding or affecting domestic conditions: housing, clothes, food and food supply, family well being</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>women&apos;s political office or involvement in political organisations e.g. the dates of a non-writing but historically significant woman&apos;s election to office (Only major first events will be listed in the National and International Events column--e.g. Lady Astor as first woman to take her seat in the House of Commons)</xhtml:li> 
                </xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:p>Writing Climate</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:ul>
                    <xhtml:li>texts and events associated with male writers</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>texts and events associated with non-British women writers</xhtml:li> 
                    <xhtml:li>information about copyright, print technology, etc.</xhtml:li>
                </xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:p>British Women&apos;s Writing</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:ul>
                    <xhtml:li>texts and events associated with British women writers</xhtml:li>
                    <xhtml:li>material conditions affecting British women&apos;s writing</xhtml:li> 
                </xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;nationalInternational&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;July 1800&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Combination Acts outlawed trade unions and strikes.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;nationalInternational&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;29 September 1938&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Munich Pact granted the Sudetenland region of Czechoslovakia to Germany.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;socialclimate&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1889&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Informal alliance between WCG and Women&apos;s Trade Union Association.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;socialclimate&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1730&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;First pair of cotton stockings ever made in England, at Nottingham, initiate the manufacture of hosiery.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;writingclimate&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1891&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Printing began at Kelmscott Press, founded by William Morris and Emery Walker.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;writingclimate&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1763&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Smart, Christopher. A Song to David.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;BritishWomenWriters&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1978&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Allnutt, Gillian. The Rag and Bone Man&apos;s Daughter Imagines a Happy Family.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>Please note that the preceding two examples have been automatically processed from bibliographic citations and would never have been entered as chronEvents on the project.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;BritishWomenWriters&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;1792&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;Elizabeth Inchbald met William Godwin, writer, radical reformer, and rationalist philosopher.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;BritishWomenWriters&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;August 1949&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;An anonymous gift from the Society of Authors enabled ME and her husband to spend a holiday in Ireland . The journal she wrote on holiday was sent to her benefactor, Winifred Bryher.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
                <xhtml:p>The chronColumn attribute values are not always conceptually clean when it comes to tagging actual research. Please fill out the attribute according to the column that you think best represents the chronology item at hand. If you do want to question the category you have used, please use a research note to do so.</xhtml:p>
                <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONSTRUCT CHRONCOLUMN=&quot;BritishWomenWriters&quot;&gt;&lt;DATE CERTAINTY=&quot;cert&quot;&gt;February 1938&lt;/&gt;&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;The Spinster began publication, campaigning for pensions for unmarried working women at 55.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;researchNote&gt;SRF: I have put this in the BWW column; should it be in writing climate instead? Or possibly even socialClimate?&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
                <choice>
                    <value>NATIONALINTERNATIONAL</value>
                    <value>WOMENWRITERS</value>
                    <value>WRITINGCLIMATE</value>
                    <value>SOCIALCLIMATE</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>        
        <optional>
            <attribute name="CHRONCOLUMN1">
                <choice>
                    <value>NATIONALINTERNATIONAL1</value>
                    <value>WOMENWRITERS1</value>
                    <value>WRITINGCLIMATE1</value>
                    <value>SOCIALCLIMATE1</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="CHRONCOLUMN2">
                <choice>
                    <value>NATIONALINTERNATIONAL2</value>
                    <value>WOMENWRITERS2</value>
                    <value>WRITINGCLIMATE2</value>
                    <value>SOCIALCLIMATE2</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="CHRONCOLUMN3">
                <choice>
                    <value>NATIONALINTERNATIONAL3</value>
                    <value>WOMENWRITERS3</value>
                    <value>WRITINGCLIMATE3</value>
                    <value>SOCIALCLIMATE3</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>        
    </define>
    
    <define name="relevance-attributes">
        <optional>
            <attribute name="RELEVANCE">
                <choice>
                    <value>SELECTIVE</value>
                    <value>PERIOD</value>
                    <value>DECADE</value>
                    <value>COMPREHENSIVE</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="RELEVANCE1">
                <choice>
                    <value>SELECTIVE1</value>
                    <value>PERIOD1</value>
                    <value>DECADE1</value>
                    <value>COMPREHENSIVE1</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="RELEVANCE2">
                <choice>
                    <value>SELECTIVE2</value>
                    <value>PERIOD2</value>
                    <value>DECADE2</value>
                    <value>COMPREHENSIVE2</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="RELEVANCE3">
                <choice>
                    <value>SELECTIVE3</value>
                    <value>PERIOD3</value>
                    <value>DECADE3</value>
                    <value>COMPREHENSIVE3</value>
                </choice>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
    </define>

    <define name="chronProse-element">
        <element name="CHRONPROSE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">ChronProse is an element that briefly describes the essential facts of a chronology event.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>chronProse</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>ChronProse is an element that briefly describes the essential facts of a chronology event.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>chronProse should contain no more than one or two pithy sentences so that its appearance will be suitable to the layout and conceptual framing of either print or electronic chronologies.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>chronProse in contained in a chronStruct and must be preceded by a date element. ChronProse contains complete sentences.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Always use full past tense in a chronProse element rather than telegraphic style:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;CHRONPROSE&gt;The term suffragette was first used in the Daily Mail.&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>In this example, the expression &quot;was first used&quot; is preferable to &quot;first used.&quot;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Should I repeat the date of a chronology event inside the chronProse? As a rule, no. However, there will be times where you feel that you need to contextualize a date or provide an alternative or extra date in your chronProse. Feel free to do this, tagging the date only if you feel it vital that it be tagged from the research/retrieval perspective, but make sure that the date you want the chronology item to be sorted under is in the date element of your chronStruct.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <!-- <ref name="rs-element"/> repeated in div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="corr-element"/> repeated in div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="emph-element"/> repeated in div1 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="foreign-element"/> repeated in div0 inclusion-->
                        <!-- <ref name="soCalled-element"/> repeated in div0 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="title-element"/> repeated in div0 inclusion -->
                        <!-- <ref name="quote-element"/> repeated in div1 inclusion -->
                        <ref name="l-element"/>
                        <ref name="lg-element"/>
                        <ref name="dateStruct-element"/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <ref name="dateRange-element"/>
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="dataStruct-element">
        <element name="DATASTRUCT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">A dataStruct is a container element for one or more individual pieces of tabular data on the project.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>dataStruct</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>A dataStruct is a container element for one or more individual pieces of tabular data on the project.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>A dataStruct can appear inside a Div2--production, reception, or textualFeatures or a Div3 inside Writing documents. In Biography documents, it can appear in either a Div2 or a Div3. In Events documents, a dataStruct can appear only inside a chronEvent. No matter where it appears, a dataStruct must contain one or more dataItems.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;DATASTRUCT&gt;&lt;DATAITEM&gt;&lt;BIRTHNAME&gt;&lt;SURNAME&gt;Costelloe, &lt;/&gt;&lt;GIVEN&gt;Rachel&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;GIVEN&gt;Mary&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;DATAITME&gt;&lt;MARRIED WROTEORPUBLISHEDAS="wrotepublishedAsYes"&gt;Strachey&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>dataStructs are currently used on the project primarily for recording names and other types of consistent tabular information. If you plan to use a dataStruct, make sure that the tabular information you enter will make sense in the context of your document. Often it is better to write a sentence that to rely on your reader being able to make sense of disjointed pieces of information.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <mixed>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <ref name="dataItem-element"/>
                </oneOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </mixed>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="dataItem-element">
        <element name="DATAITEM">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">dataItem is an element that contains an individual piece of tabular information.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>dataItem</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>dataItem is an element that contains an individual piece of tabular information.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>dataItem contains only tabular information. Information that is written in full sentences is more appropriately placed in a paragraph element.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>dataItem is always contained within a dataStruct element</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dataStruct&gt;&lt;dataItem&gt;&lt;married&gt;Ward&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;dataItem&gt;&lt;married&gt;Smith&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Open a new dataItem for each discrete piece of tabular information. For example, the contents of a married element (in personName) might look as follows:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Question: Should birthname use separate dataItems for patronym and given names? Answer: No. For the purposes of the project a birthname is considered a single dataItem.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;dataStruct&gt;&lt;dataItem&gt;&lt;birthName&gt;&lt;surname&gt;Barrett&lt;/&gt;&lt;given&gt;Elizabeth&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <text/>
                        <ref name="dateStruct-element"/>
                        <ref name="dateRange-element"/>
                        <ref name="date-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="name-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="place-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="orgName-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="rs-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="time-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="corr-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="emph-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="foreign-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="soCalled-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="title-element"/>-->
                        <!--<ref name="quote-element"/>-->
                        <ref name="l-element"/>
                        <ref name="lg-element"/>
                        <!--<ref name="topic-element"/>-->
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="shortProse-element">
        <element name="SHORTPROSE">
            <!-- LS to MP: No documentation for this even though it is mentioned many times in the documentation for other tags. -->
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <mixed>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <ref name="p-element"/>
                </oneOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </mixed>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="standard-element">
        <!-- exclusion: datestruct, daterange, date,
                                    keywordclass, name, orgname, place, topic (bio DTD)-->
        <element name="STANDARD">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Standard is an element used to record the standard name by which a woman writer is known. It prefaces a writing or biography document and should reflect the name under which she wrote or the name chosen as standard by the <em>Feminist Companion</em> or the <em>Drabble Oxford Companion</em>.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>Standard</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Standard is an element used to record the standard name by which a woman writer is known. It prefaces a writing or biography document and should reflect the name under which she wrote or the name chosen as standard by the <em>Feminist Companion</em> or the <em>Drabble Oxford Companion</em>.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Bibliography Database</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>This element occurs in the bio and writing documents.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>This element accepts as sub-elements all those which have been identified as globally available including name, title, and date, but it will be highly unusual for any of these to be used within Standard. You need not duplicate your work by including a name tag within Standard.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The name you choose as the Standard will influence which initials you choose to use throughout the document. Any of the names that appear in capitals should be marked with an initial so that they can be properly expanded within the document at a later date. For example, Harriet Beecher Stowe becomes HBS, Adelaide O'Keefe becomes AOK, and Marie Catherine de Villedieu becomes MCV.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>When entering texts by BWWs, IWWs, or MWs into the bibliography database, you must use the standard name for all entries. There are other fields available in the bibliography database to record pseudonyms, etc, or to indicate that a work was published anonymously.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you are entering secondary sources into the bibliography database, use the name under which the scholar publishes in the standard name field. Try to be consistent in the way you enter secondary source authors' names.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you disagree with the standard name chosen by the <em>Feminist Companion</em> or the <em>Oxford Companion</em>, please take up your concerns with a volume author or one of the post docs, who will relay the query to a volume author.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If your standard name is demarcated by either single quotation marks or parentheses remove them. If you are dealing with a British woman writer's document please capture the information that these bits of typesetting imply in the appropriate tags in personName--single quotations demarcate pseuds and parentheses demarcate surnames at birth.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="WROTEORPUBLISHEDAS">
                    <a:defaultValue>WROTEPUBLISHEDASYES</a:defaultValue>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <interleave>
                <text/>
                <ref name="Div0narrow-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="biogProse-element">
        <element name="BIOGPROSE">
            <!-- LS to MP: No documentation for this. -->
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <text/>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="worksCited-element">
        <element name="WORKSCITED">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The WorksCited is an informal but complete list of all sources used in the writing of biography and writing documents. You should ensure that all of these sources are also entered in the bibliography database.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>WorksCited</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The WorksCited is an informal but complete list of all sources used in the writing of biography and writing documents. You should ensure that all of these sources are also entered in the bibliography database.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The WorksCited appears at the end of the document, outside of the last Div1 and before the Feminist Companion entry in those documents which include these entries. Each individual source must be placed within a Source tag.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Here&apos;s how your worksCited should look:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Wyatt-Brown, Anne M. Barbara Pym: A Critical Biography. 1992.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The period goes after the author name (which is inverted); a short title is used (assuming that the full title is recorded in the bibliography database) without a title tag and followed by a period; a period also appears after the year. Provide enough bibliographic information so that the source can be easily identified: for example, be certain to specify which edition you are using if a work has been reprinted in several different editions. Full bibliographic information should be entered in the bibliography database.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <interleave>
                <oneOrMore>
                    <ref name="source-element"/>
                </oneOrMore>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </interleave>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="source-element">
        <element name="SOURCE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">source describes the original source for the information contained with a manuscript description.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>source</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>source describes the original source for the information contained with a manuscript description.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;SOURCE&gt;Cutbill, Jonathan, Introduction in Fitzroy, A.T. Despised and Rejected, 1988 edition&lt;/SOURCE&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <mixed>
                <!--<text/>-->
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </mixed>
        </element>
    </define>

    <!-- Definition of elements mentioned in inclusions -->

    <define name="researchNote-element">
        <element name="RESEARCHNOTE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">ResearchNote is available everywhere, and it allows us to comment among ourselves on the work at hand; not to be confused with scholarNotes that will be readable by end users, the contents of this element will be seen only by the eyes of Orlandians.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>ResearchNote</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>ResearchNote is available everywhere, and it allows us to comment among ourselves on the work at hand; not to be confused with scholarNotes that will be readable by end users, the contents of this element will be seen only by the eyes of Orlandians.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Occurring anywhere, this element can contain anything but should be prefaced by the initials of the person writing the comments.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>ResearchNotes should be placed in the least conspicuous place.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>If you encounter ResearchNotes that refer to completed actions of negligible importance, feel free to delete them. However, you will want to keep in researchNotes that say things like "this is a typo/no it&apos;s not" because they may save us a step later on. Of course, researchNotes that have substantive information or queries about sources or research processes should stay in. When in doubt, leave it in.</xhtml:p>
            <mixed>
                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
            </mixed>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="bibCit-element">
        <element name="BIBCIT">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The element named bibCit is designed to capture bibliographical information in much the same way as an MLA parenthetical citation and should always reside within a bibCits container tag.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>bibCit</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The element named bibCit is designed to capture bibliographical information in much the same way as an MLA parenthetical citation and should always reside within a bibCits container tag.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>BibCits are available nearly everywhere from the Div0 level down.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>All research information and quotations must be followed by a bibcit indicating the source of this information or quotation. There are a few exceptions to this rule. Discussions of BWW&apos;s texts within the textual features section of writing documents do not require bibcits if they are the product of the Project member writing the document.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The Orlando Project&apos;s bibcits follow MLA style: Pedersen 90; Holton, Suffrage 107-8; qtd. in Hume 76. However, much of this information, including author&apos;s name, short title, and the abbreviation &quot;qtd. in,&quot; will be stored in attributes and rendered through various stylesheets. In its final form within an SGML document, the text of a bibcit will contain page numbers only, and may sometimes even be empty if no page number is required (in the case of one-volume alphabetically arranged reference books, for example).</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>BibCits go just inside the end tag of whatever piece of information they apply to. In events documents, for example, this will be the end tag for the whole chronStruct. Bibcits for ChronStructs should appear just before the closing tag; bibCits for chronEvents should occur just before the closing tag; and bibCits that refer to entire paragraphs should appear outside of the closing &lt;/p&gt; tag but before the closing shortProse tag unless the bibcit is specific to a single para in a multi-paragraph shortProse in which case it goes inside&lt;/p&gt;. You need to have a biibCit after each direct quotation, and please use them as frequently as necessary throughout the prose writing in your doc to make the job easier for source checkers.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>This element is equivalent to other globally available elements such as title, keywordClass, scholarNote, and researchNote.The bibcit tag has three different attributes: BIBCIT PLACEHOLDER: the bibcit placeholder retains the text of the original, MLA-style bibcit. DBREF: the dbref, or database reference number, is the number of the corresponding bibliographic citation for the source cited; this number can be determined by looking up the source in the bibliography database.QTDIN: qtdin is available for those quotations which would be preceded by &quot;qtd. in&quot;; for example, if you are providing a quotation from a BWW and your source is a secondary source which imbeds this quotation within its own text. When you quote from a quoted passage in a secondary source (eg, a biography which quotes from diaries, letters, etc), then you choose the attribute &quot;qtd. in = yes&quot;. This will get rendered down the road, probably as &quot;qtd. in,&quot; when the dbref numbers are converted to author name, short title format. You do not need to write in the words &apos;qtd. in&quot;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you are writing documents, fill in the bibcit attributes as you proceed. As a courtesy to future source-checkers, provide the author and/or short title in both the bibcit placeholder and in the actual text of the bibcit proper; source checkers will delete this information from the bibcit text as they check each reference.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>BibCits and Quotes:All quote tags should be followed by a bibCit as if the sentence had normal spacing without the bibCit.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>It was originally opened by Queen Victoria as the People&apos;s Palace, a place of &lt;quote Direct=y&gt;rational and instructive entertainment and of artistic enjoyment&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;bibCit&gt;&lt;/bibCit&gt;for the people of East London.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Note: Unlike the MLA style of documentation, there should be no space between the bibCit and whatever goes before it, whether that is a closing quote tag or end-of-sentence punctuation. There is no space between the end of the quote and the beginning of the bibCit, but there is a space after the bibCit before the following word.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If a single source is quoted multiple times in one sentence, the bibCit should immediately follow the end of the sentence. Note: if source is used to supply information beyond the quotation, then a bibCit must ALSO be included according to standard bibCit practice.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If a person other than the author of the work cited in the bibCit is quoted then use the QtdInYes value on the &quot;qtd. in&quot; attributes for the bibCit. If both the author of the of the work cited in the bibCit and another person are quoted in a single quote tag, then embed one quote tag inside another. Do not adopt &quot;qtd. in&quot; practice for such examples.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Page ranges should not repeat #s (e.g. 65-6 NOT 65-66)</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Every quote should have a bibCit.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&quot;Qtd. in&quot; should be represented in the attribute when necessary.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>When you use the abbreviation ff in a bibCit, it does not need a period.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Spacing should read properly when the bibCit is removed.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you are using two books by one author in the same document, use short titles to distinguish between the two: lastname short title ##. Ensure that you are providing the correct dbref number for each separate work in the respective dbref attribute.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>BLC shelfmarks. There is no need to include shelfmarks for 20th century material unless something is very rare. Our practice on this project has been to use them when necessary--for rare early material and more often for nineteenth-century material--but this inconsistent approach does not present any problems.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Here&apos;s how you should handle information that is derived from a footnote in your primary source:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Crook 127n9</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>It takes no punctuation and no spaces (except between the author&apos;s last name and the page reference). You should use this only when the information you are using has been taken from the footnote.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Here&apos;s how you should handle citations from continuously paginated multi-volume references: short title volume number (year): page number</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Athanæum 1370 (1854): 117</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Include the year where possible. If you have only the year or only the volume, then use the following guide:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Punch 254: 62</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>TLS 1963: 941</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you are working with a multi-volume text whose page numbers begin at one with each new volume, then follow this guide: Publication volume/issue# (year): page number. So an example would look like this: Writers&apos; Unlimited 12 (1999): 40.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>For single volume alphabetically-arranged reference works, page numbers are not required provided that it is clear which article is being used. For example, biographical dictionaries do not require page numbers unless you are using an article about someone other than the subject of your document. Some examples of single-volume alphabetically arranged reference works which do not require page numbers are:</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:ul>
                <xhtml:li>Berney, K.A., ed. Contemporary Women Dramatists, 1994</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Boylan, Henry, ed. A Dictionary of Irish Biography, 1978</xhtml:li>     
                <xhtml:li>Brady, Anne M. and Brian Cleeve, A Biographical Dictionary of Irish Writers, 1985</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Buck, Clare, ed. Bloomsbury Guide to Women&apos;s Literature,1992</xhtml:li> 
                <xhtml:li>Harris, Sharon, ed. American Women Writers to 1800, 1996</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Hartnoll, Phyllis, ed. The Oxford Companion to Theatre 4th ed., 1983</xhtml:li> 
                <xhtml:li>Klein, Kathleen Gregory, ed. Great Women Mystery Writers, 1994</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Joanne Shattock, The Oxford Guide to British Women Writers, 1993</xhtml:li> 
                <xhtml:li>Paul Schleuter and June Schleuter, An Encyclopedia of British Women Writers, 1988</xhtml:li>
                <xhtml:li>Janet Todd, ed. Dictionary of British Women Writers, 1989</xhtml:li> 
                <xhtml:li>Janet Todd, ed. A Dictionary of British and American Women Writers, 1660-1800, 1985</xhtml:li>
            </xhtml:ul>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Q: How do I bibCit a book&apos;s publication as event when my source is the book itself? A: Don&apos;t worry about adding a bibCit in this situation; a researchNote specifying the source of the information (the title page of the book, for instance) will make more sense than trying to manufacture a bibCit.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>For multi-volume reference works, include both volume and page numbers. You must also specify which edition of the reference work you are using. This information does not need to appear in the bibcit itself, but it must appear in the corresponding bibrecord in the bibl db, and you must make sure that the dbref number you provide is for the correct edition.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="PLACEHOLDER"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="DBREF">
                    <data type="NMTOKEN"/>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="QTDIN">
                    <value>QTDINYES</value>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <text/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="scholarNote-element">
        <element name="SCHOLARNOTE">
            <!-- LS to MP: No documentation for this even though it is mentioned in the documentation for other tags. -->
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <oneOrMore>
                <ref name="p-element"/>
            </oneOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="keywordClass-element">
        <element name="KEYWORDCLASS">
            <!-- LS to MP: No documentation for this. -->
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="KEYWORDTYPE"/>
                <![CDATA[]]>
            </optional>
            <text/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="bibCits-element">
        <element name="BIBCITS">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">bibCits is a container for one or more bibcit tag(s).</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>bibCits</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>bibcits is a container for one or more bibcit tag(s).</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;BIBCITS&gt;&lt;BIBCIT PLACEHOLDER="Watkins" DBREF="69025"&gt;&lt;/BIBCIT&gt;&lt;/BIBCITS&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                    <ref name="bibCit-element"/>
                    <ref name="researchNote-element"/>
                </choice>
            </zeroOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="lb-element">
        <element name="LB">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">lb marks the start of a new (typographic) line in some edition or version of a text.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>lb</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>lb marks the start of a new (typographic) line in some edition or version of a text.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <text/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="sic-element">
        <element name="SIC">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">This element is left over from the TEI set of elements and is meant to be used in the same way that you would use a [sic] tag in regular prose. For our purposes, we have devised a set of practice directives to guide you in your use of this element. It is primarily a formatting tag which inserts the word [sic] in rendered text.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>Sic</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>This element is left over from the TEI set of elements and is meant to be used in the same way that you would use a [sic] tag in regular prose. For our purposes, we have devised a set of practice directives to guide you in your use of this element. It is primarily a formatting tag which inserts the word [sic] in rendered text.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>This element should encapsulate only the word that to which it applies.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The sic tag&apos;s corr attribute need not be filled in.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not use sic tag for any &quot;mistakes&quot; that were intentional, possibly playful, misuses of language; that were simply the result of non-standardised spelling conventions; or that are contained in other tags and have been regularized appropriately (eg., *Pomes Penyeach*, *Our Exagmination round His Factification for Incamination of Work in Progress*, Shakspeare in a name tag with attribute standard=Shakespeare, William).</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Sic tags should only be used in title tags if in delivery we want to record (with &quot;[sic]&quot;) the misspelling in the title; judgement calls will have to be made in these cases, please consult the appropriate VA or PDF if unsure.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Do not use the sic tag to indicate divergence of project punctuation-practice from the cited text (eg., ellipsis that appears in quoted text as &quot;...&quot; should be rendered in our documents as &quot;. . .&quot; and should not be enclosed in a sic tag).</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="CORR"/>
            </optional>
            <text/>
        </element>
    </define>
    
    <define name="job-element">
        <element name="JOB">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Job is meant to capture the types of employment done by women writers and their families. We are interested in comparing the kinds of jobs women did in different historical periods and the kinds of jobs family members did. We want to facilitate research, for example, on the influence of living in a parsonage on women writers and would therefore like to track women who had fathers and mothers who were preachers.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>job</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Job is meant to capture the types of employment done by women writers and their families. We are interested in comparing the kinds of jobs women did in different historical periods and the kinds of jobs family members did. We want to facilitate research, for example, on the influence of living in a parsonage on women writers and would therefore like to track women who had fathers and mothers who were preachers.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>This sub-element should be placed around the word or phrase describing the job.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Job is available as a sub-element under occupation and member. It has one optional attribute named Reg which allows you to standardize the name of a job if you have been unable to do so in your prose.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>She&lt;job REG="nurse"&gt;attended to the sick&lt;/&gt;during her years in Vichy.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>She was a &lt;job&gt;teacher&lt;/&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>She worked as a &lt;job&gt;nurse&lt;/&gt; during WWI.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Only tag job within occupation if the job belonged to the subject of the biography. Only tag job within member if the job belonged to the subject of the member tag. We will want to generate separate lists of jobs done by British Women Writers and jobs done by, for example, their mothers or husbands.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Be careful with those who hold jobs at British universities, especially Cambridge and Oxford. IMG notes that the title of professor is somewhat rare there and cannot be the standard form for anyone who teaches at those institutions. Use academic as the regularised job attribute; the prose may read things like &quot;lecturer&quot; or &quot;reader&quot; or (at Cambridge or Oxford) will read &quot;fellow and tutor&quot; or &quot;fellow and lecturer&quot;.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Try to phrase your discussion of her job in such a way that allows you to place the job element around the one word noun rather than a verb or phrase. For example, use &quot;She was a teacher&quot; instead of &quot;She taught.&quot; If such phrasing is impossible, use the currentAlternativeTerm attribute attached to job, to enter the correct title of the job.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>AA worked in &lt;job CURRENTALTERNATIVETERM=&quot;ceramicist&quot;&gt;ceramics&lt;/&gt; and &lt;job CURRENTALTERNATIVETERM=&quot;designer&quot;>design&lt;/&gt; at the Chelsea Pottery.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing activities are not jobs. See occupation.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Troubleshooting</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Question: What if all I know is where she worked but not what her job was?</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Answer: Include whatever information is available, tag the employer and try to phrase the sentence in general terms to capture something of the job.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>PMS began a &lt;job&gt;career in fashion&lt;/&gt; and worked at &lt;employer&gt;&lt;orgName&gt;Christian Dior&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="FAMILYBUSINESS" a:defaultValue="FAMILYBUSINESSYES">
                    <!-- check att DEFAULT value -->
                    <value>FAMILYBUSINESSYES</value>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="CURRENTALTERNATIVETERM"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="HISTORICALTERM"/>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="HISTORICALTERMCONTEXTDATE"
                    a:annotation="The context and time period in which the historical term was in use"/>
            </optional>
            <ref name="reg-attribute"/>
            <mixed>
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <choice>
                        <!--<text/>-->
                        <element name="OCCUPATION">
                            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
                            <mixed>
                                <oneOrMore>
                                    <choice>
                                        <zeroOrMore>
                                            <ref name="chronStruct-element"/>
                                        </zeroOrMore>
                                    </choice>
                                </oneOrMore>
                                <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                                <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>
                            </mixed>
                        </element>
                        <!-- member inclusion elements overlap -->
                        <ref name="Div0-inclusion"/>
                        <ref name="Div1-inclusion"/>                        
                    </choice>
                </zeroOrMore>
            </mixed>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="tGenre-element">
        <element name="TGENRE">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">GenreName (or tGenre) is used to tag the name of the genre according to a project-generated list of genre names.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>genre</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>GenreName (or tGenre) is used to tag the name of the genre according to a project-generated list of genre names.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>This element should surround only the descriptive title of the genre name.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>There are no mandatory or optional sub-elements for this element although it has an ancillary element in GenreIssue. There are two optional attributes for this element named genreName and proposedAlternativeName. The first allows you to indicate specifically the kind of text you are talking about in situations where you have been unable to work the genre name elegantly into your prose. The second allows you to propose a genre name to the list of Orlando-approved genre names if no other appropriate name can be found on the pick list.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>The values for the genreName attribute are as follows: &quot;abridgement, &quot; &quot;aCLef, &quot; &quot;acrostic,&quot; &quot;adaptation,&quot; &quot;adventureWriting,&quot; &quot;advertisingCopy,&quot; &quot;afterPiece,&quot; &quot;afterword,&quot; &quot;agitProp,&quot; &quot;allegory,&quot; &quot;almanac,&quot; &quot;anacreontic,&quot; &quot;anagram,&quot; &quot;annotation,&quot; &quot;answer,&quot; &quot;anthem,&quot; &quot;anthology,&quot; &quot;antiromance,&quot; &quot;aphorism,&quot; &quot;apology,&quot; &quot;artCriticism,&quot; &quot;autobiography,&quot; &quot;ballad,&quot; &quot;ballade,&quot; &quot;balladOpera,&quot; &quot;ballet,&quot; &quot;bergamasque,&quot; &quot;bestiary,&quot; &quot;biblicalParaphrase,&quot; &quot;bildungsroman,&quot; &quot;biographicalDictionary,&quot; &quot;biography,&quot; &quot;bisexualFiction,&quot; &quot;blackComedy,&quot; &quot;boutsRimes,&quot; &quot;broadside,&quot; &quot;burletta,&quot; &quot;cabaret,&quot; &quot;captivityNarrative,&quot; &quot;catechism,&quot; &quot;chapbook,&quot; &quot;character,&quot; &quot;charade,&quot; &quot;childrensLiterature,&quot; &quot;clerihew,&quot; &quot;closetdrama,&quot; &quot;colouringBook,&quot; &quot;comedy,&quot; &quot;comedyOfHumours,&quot; &quot;comedyOfIntrigue,&quot; &quot;comedyOfManners,&quot; &quot;comedyOfMenace,&quot; &quot;comicBook,&quot; &quot;comingOut,&quot; &quot;commonplaceBook,&quot; &quot;companion,&quot; &quot;computerProgram,&quot; &quot;conditionOfEnglandNovel,&quot; &quot;conductLiterature,&quot; &quot;cookbook,&quot; &quot;courtshipFiction,&quot; &quot;criminology,&quot; &quot;dedication,&quot; &quot;detective,&quot; &quot;devotional,&quot; &quot;dialogueOrDebate,&quot; &quot;diary,&quot; &quot;dialogueOfTheDead,&quot; &quot;dictionary,&quot; &quot;didactic,&quot; &quot;directory,&quot; &quot;dissertation,&quot; &quot;documentary,&quot; &quot;domestic,&quot; &quot;drama,&quot; &quot;dramaticMonologue,&quot; &quot;dreamVision,&quot; &quot;dystopia,&quot; &quot;eclogue,&quot; &quot;editing,&quot; &quot;elegy,&quot; &quot;encyclopaedia,&quot; &quot;epic,&quot; &quot;epicTheatre,&quot; &quot;epigram,&quot; &quot;epilogue,&quot; &quot;episodicLiterature,&quot; &quot;epistle,&quot; &quot;epistolary,&quot; &quot;epitaph,&quot; &quot;epithalamium,&quot; &quot;epyllion,&quot; &quot;eroticaPornography,&quot; &quot;essay,&quot; &quot;eulogy,&quot; &quot;exhibitionCatalogue,&quot; &quot;expressionistWriting,&quot; &quot;fable,&quot; &quot;fabliau,&quot; &quot;FairyTale,&quot; &quot;fantasy,&quot; &quot;farce,&quot; &quot;feminist,&quot; &quot;feministTheory,&quot; &quot;fiction,&quot; &quot;filmTVScript,&quot; &quot;folkSong,&quot; &quot;gardeningBook,&quot; &quot;genealogy,&quot; &quot;georgic,&quot; &quot;ghostStory,&quot; &quot;giftbook,&quot; &quot;gothic,&quot; &quot;governmentReport,&quot; &quot;grammar,&quot; &quot;graveyardPoetry,&quot; &quot;guerillaTheatre,&quot; &quot;guidebook,&quot; &quot;hagiography,&quot; &quot;haiku,&quot; &quot;harlequinade,&quot; &quot;heroic,&quot; &quot;historical,&quot; &quot;history,&quot; &quot;hymn,&quot; &quot;imitation,&quot; &quot;improvisation,&quot; &quot;industrialNovel,&quot; &quot;introduction,&quot; &quot;journalism,&quot; &quot;juvenilia,&quot; &quot;kitchenSinkDrama,&quot; &quot;kunstleroman,&quot; &quot;lais,&quot; &quot;lampoon,&quot; &quot;legalWriting,&quot; &quot;legendFolkTale,&quot; &quot;lesbian,&quot; &quot;letter,&quot; &quot;lettersFromTheDeadToTheLiving,&quot; &quot;libretto,&quot; &quot;literaryCriticism,&quot; &quot;liturgy,&quot; &quot;love,&quot; &quot;lyric,&quot; &quot;magicRealist,&quot; &quot;manifesto,&quot; &quot;manual,&quot; &quot;map,&quot; &quot;masque,&quot; &quot;medicalWriting,&quot; &quot;melodrama,&quot; &quot;mixedMedia,&quot; &quot;mockForms,&quot; &quot;monologue,&quot; &quot;moralityMysteryPlay,&quot; &quot;multimedia,&quot; &quot;musicology,&quot; &quot;mystery,&quot; &quot;myth,&quot; &quot;narrativePoetry,&quot; &quot;nationalistFiction,&quot; &quot;nationalTale,&quot; &quot;notebook,&quot; &quot;novel,&quot; &quot;novella,&quot; &quot;nurseryRhyme,&quot; &quot;obituary,&quot; &quot;occasionalPoetry,&quot; &quot;ode,&quot; &quot;oneActPlay,&quot; &quot;opera,&quot; &quot;oratorio,&quot; &quot;oriental,&quot; &quot;pageant,&quot; &quot;panegyric,&quot; &quot;pantomime,&quot; &quot;parable,&quot; &quot;paratexts,&quot; &quot;parliamentaryReport,&quot; &quot;parody,&quot; &quot;pastoral,&quot; &quot;pedagogy,&quot; &quot;performancePoetry,&quot; &quot;periodical,&quot; &quot;petition,&quot; &quot;philosophical,&quot; &quot;philosophy,&quot; &quot;picaresque,&quot; &quot;pindaric,&quot; &quot;poetry,&quot; &quot;polemic,&quot; &quot;politicalWriting,&quot; &quot;popular,&quot; &quot;prayer,&quot; &quot;prefatoryPiece,&quot; &quot;programNotes,&quot; &quot;proletarianWriting,&quot; &quot;prologue,&quot; &quot;propaganda,&quot; &quot;prophecy,&quot; &quot;psalm,&quot; &quot;psychoanalytical,&quot; &quot;quiz,&quot; &quot;radioDrama,&quot; &quot;realist,&quot; &quot;regional,&quot; &quot;religious,&quot; &quot;review,&quot; &quot;revue,&quot; &quot;riddle,&quot; &quot;romance,&quot; &quot;sageWriting,&quot; &quot;satire,&quot; &quot;scholarship,&quot; &quot;schoolFiction,&quot; &quot;scienceFiction,&quot; &quot;scientificWriting,&quot; &quot;scrapbook,&quot; &quot;sensationNovel,&quot; &quot;sensibility,&quot; &quot;sentimental,&quot; &quot;sequel,&quot; &quot;sermon,&quot; &quot;sexualAwakeningFiction,&quot; &quot;shortStory,&quot; &quot;silverForkNovel,&quot; &quot;sketch,&quot; &quot;sketchbook,&quot; &quot;slaveNarrative,&quot; &quot;socialScience,&quot; &quot;song,&quot; &quot;sonnet,&quot; &quot;speech,&quot; &quot;stageReview,&quot; &quot;testimony,&quot; &quot;textbook,&quot; &quot;theatreOfCruelty,&quot; &quot;theatreOfTheAbsurd,&quot; &quot;theology,&quot; &quot;thesaurus,&quot; &quot;thriller,&quot; &quot;topographicalPoetry,&quot; &quot;tractPamphlet,&quot; &quot;tragedy,&quot; &quot;tragiComedy,&quot; &quot;translation,&quot; &quot;travelWriting,&quot; &quot;treatise,&quot; &quot;utopia,&quot; &quot;verseNovel,&quot; &quot;vignette,&quot; &quot;villanelle,&quot; &quot;youngAdultWriting.&quot;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;tGenre&gt;metrical psalms&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;tGenre&gt;Senecan tragedy&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;tGenre&gt;verse lives&lt;/&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Practice Issues</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>If multiple genre names are required for a single text, then you must nest elements inside each other</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>If you have a simply named genre such as poetry or drama (which may be more precisely named a mode of literature) you should use the ProposedAlternativeName field in the attribute attached to genreName and fill in the appropriate word. This does not need to be done for every occurrence of the word; once per chronStruct, or in short document, one per document should be fine.</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="GENRENAME">
                    <choice>
                        <value>ABRIDGEMENT</value>
                        <value>ACLEF</value>
                        <value>ACROSTIC</value>
                        <value>ADAPTATION</value>
                        <value>ADVENTUREWRITING</value>
                        <value>ADVERTISINGCOPY</value>
                        <value>AFTERPIECE</value>
                        <value>AFTERWORD</value>
                        <value>AGITPROP</value>
                        <value>ALLEGORY</value>
                        <value>ALMANAC</value>
                        <value>ANACREONTIC</value>
                        <value>ANAGRAM</value>
                        <value>ANNOTATION</value>
                        <value>ANSWER</value>
                        <value>ANTHEM</value>
                        <value>ANTHOLOGY</value>
                        <value>ANTIROMANCE</value>
                        <value>APHORISM</value>
                        <value>APOLOGY</value>
                        <value>ARTCRITICISM</value>
                        <value>AUTOBIOGRAPHY</value>
                        <value>BALLAD</value>
                        <value>BALLADE</value>
                        <value>BALLADOPERA</value>
                        <value>BALLET</value>
                        <value>BERGAMASQUE</value>
                        <value>BESTIARY</value>
                        <value>BIBLICALPARAPHRASE</value>
                        <value>BILDUNGSROMAN</value>
                        <value>BIOGRAPHICALDICTIONARY</value>
                        <value>BIOGRAPHY</value>
                        <value>BISEXUALFICTION</value>
                        <value>BLACKCOMEDY</value>
                        <value>BOUTSRIMES</value>
                        <value>BROADSIDE</value>
                        <value>BURLETTA</value>
                        <value>CABARET</value>
                        <value>CAPTIVITYNARRATIVE</value>
                        <value>CATECHISM</value>
                        <value>CHAPBOOK</value>
                        <value>CHARACTER</value>
                        <value>CHARADE</value>
                        <value>CHILDRENSLITERATURE</value>
                        <value>CLERIHEW</value>
                        <value>CLOSETDRAMA</value>
                        <value>COLOURINGBOOK</value>
                        <value>COMEDY</value>
                        <value>COMEDYOFHUMOURS</value>
                        <value>COMEDYOFINTRIGUE</value>
                        <value>COMEDYOFMANNERS</value>
                        <value>COMEDYOFMENACE</value>
                        <value>COMICBOOK</value>
                        <value>COMINGOUT</value>
                        <value>COMMONPLACEBOOK</value>
                        <value>COMPANION</value>
                        <value>COMPUTERPROGRAM</value>
                        <value>CONDITIONOFENGLANDNOVEL</value>
                        <value>CONDUCTLITERATURE</value>
                        <value>COOKBOOK</value>
                        <value>COURTSHIPFICTION</value>
                        <value>CRIMINOLOGY</value>
                        <value>DEDICATION</value>
                        <value>DETECTIVE</value>
                        <value>DEVOTIONAL</value>
                        <value>DIALOGUEORDEBATE</value>
                        <value>DIARY</value>
                        <value>DIALOGUEOFTHEDEAD</value>
                        <value>DICTIONARY</value>
                        <value>DIDACTIC</value>
                        <value>DIRECTORY</value>
                        <value>DISSERTATION</value>
                        <value>DOCUMENTARY</value>
                        <value>DOMESTIC</value>
                        <value>DRAMA</value>
                        <value>DRAMATICMONOLOGUE</value>
                        <value>DREAMVISION</value>
                        <value>DYSTOPIA</value>
                        <value>ECLOGUE</value>
                        <value>EDITING</value>
                        <value>ELEGY</value>
                        <value>ENCYCLOPAEDIA</value>
                        <value>EPIC</value>
                        <value>EPICTHEATRE</value>
                        <value>EPIGRAM</value>
                        <value>EPILOGUE</value>
                        <value>EPISODICLITERATURE</value>
                        <value>EPISTLE</value>
                        <value>EPISTOLARY</value>
                        <value>EPITAPH</value>
                        <value>EPITHALAMIUM</value>
                        <value>EPYLLION</value>
                        <value>EROTICAPORNOGRAPHY</value>
                        <value>ESSAY</value>
                        <value>EULOGY</value>
                        <value>EXHIBITIONCATALOGUE</value>
                        <value>EXPRESSIONISTWRITING</value>
                        <value>FABLE</value>
                        <value>FABLIAU</value>
                        <value>FAIRYTALE</value>
                        <value>FANTASY</value>
                        <value>FARCE</value>
                        <value>FEMINIST</value>
                        <value>FEMINISTTHEORY</value>
                        <value>FICTION</value>
                        <value>FILMTVSCRIPT</value>
                        <value>FOLKSONG</value>
                        <value>GARDENINGBOOK</value>
                        <value>GENEALOGY</value>
                        <value>GEORGIC</value>
                        <value>GHOSTSTORY</value>
                        <value>GIFTBOOK</value>
                        <value>GOTHIC</value>
                        <value>GOVERNMENTREPORT</value>
                        <value>GRAMMAR</value>
                        <value>GRAVEYARDPOETRY</value>
                        <value>GUERILLATHEATRE</value>
                        <value>GUIDEBOOK</value>
                        <value>HAGIOGRAPHY</value>
                        <value>HAIKU</value>
                        <value>HARLEQUINADE</value>
                        <value>HEROIC</value>
                        <value>HISTORICAL</value>
                        <value>HISTORY</value>
                        <value>HYMN</value>
                        <value>IMITATION</value>
                        <value>IMPROVISATION</value>
                        <value>INDUSTRIALNOVEL</value>
                        <value>INTRODUCTION</value>
                        <value>JOURNALISM</value>
                        <value>JUVENILIA</value>
                        <value>KITCHENSINKDRAMA</value>
                        <value>KUNSTLERROMAN</value>
                        <value>LAIS</value>
                        <value>LAMPOON</value>
                        <value>LEGALWRITING</value>
                        <value>LEGENDFOLKTALE</value>
                        <value>LESBIAN</value>
                        <value>LETTER</value>
                        <value>LETTERSFROMTHEDEADTOTHELIVING</value>
                        <value>LIBRETTO</value>
                        <value>LITERARYCRITICISM</value>
                        <value>LITURGY</value>
                        <value>LOVE</value>
                        <value>LYRIC</value>
                        <value>MAGICREALIST</value>
                        <value>MANIFESTO</value>
                        <value>MANUAL</value>
                        <value>MAP</value>
                        <value>MASQUE</value>
                        <value>MEDICALWRITING</value>
                        <value>MELODRAMA</value>
                        <value>MIXEDMEDIA</value>
                        <value>MOCKFORMS</value>
                        <value>MONOLOGUE</value>
                        <value>MORALITYMYSTERYPLAY</value>
                        <value>MULTIMEDIA</value>
                        <value>MUSICOLOGY</value>
                        <value>MYSTERY</value>
                        <value>MYTH</value>
                        <value>NARRATIVEPOETRY</value>
                        <value>NATIONALISTFICTION</value>
                        <value>NATIONALTALE</value>
                        <value>NOTEBOOK</value>
                        <value>NOVEL</value>
                        <value>NOVELLA</value>
                        <value>NURSERYRHYME</value>
                        <value>OBITUARY</value>
                        <value>OCCASIONALPOETRY</value>
                        <value>ODE</value>
                        <value>ONEACTPLAY</value>
                        <value>OPERA</value>
                        <value>ORATORIO</value>
                        <value>ORIENTAL</value>
                        <value>PAGEANT</value>
                        <value>PANEGYRIC</value>
                        <value>PANTOMIME</value>
                        <value>PARABLE</value>
                        <value>PARATEXTS</value>
                        <value>PARLIAMENTARYREPORT</value>
                        <value>PARODY</value>
                        <value>PASTORAL</value>
                        <value>PEDAGOGY</value>
                        <value>PERFORMANCEPOETRY</value>
                        <value>PERIODICAL</value>
                        <value>PETITION</value>
                        <value>PHILOSOPHICAL</value>
                        <value>PHILOSOPHY</value>
                        <value>PICARESQUE</value>
                        <value>PINDARIC</value>
                        <value>POETRY</value>
                        <value>POLEMIC</value>
                        <value>POLITICALWRITING</value>
                        <value>POPULAR</value>
                        <value>PRAYER</value>
                        <value>PREFATORYPIECE</value>
                        <value>PROGRAMNOTES</value>
                        <value>PROLETARIANWRITING</value>
                        <value>PROLOGUE</value>
                        <value>PROPAGANDA</value>
                        <value>PROPHECY</value>
                        <value>PSALM</value>
                        <value>PSYCHOANALYTICAL</value>
                        <value>QUIZ</value>
                        <value>RADIODRAMA</value>
                        <value>REALIST</value>
                        <value>REGIONAL</value>
                        <value>RELIGIOUS</value>
                        <value>REVIEW</value>
                        <value>REVUE</value>
                        <value>RIDDLE</value>
                        <value>ROMANCE</value>
                        <value>SAGEWRITING</value>
                        <value>SATIRE</value>
                        <value>SCHOLARSHIP</value>
                        <value>SCHOOLFICTION</value>
                        <value>SCIENCEFICTION</value>
                        <value>SCIENTIFICWRITING</value>
                        <value>SCRAPBOOK</value>
                        <value>SENSATIONNOVEL</value>
                        <value>SENSIBILITY</value>
                        <value>SENTIMENTAL</value>
                        <value>SEQUEL</value>
                        <value>SERMON</value>
                        <value>SEXUALAWAKENINGFICTION</value>
                        <value>SHORTSTORY</value>
                        <value>SILVERFORKNOVEL</value>
                        <value>SKETCH</value>
                        <value>SKETCHBOOK</value>
                        <value>SLAVENARRATIVE</value>
                        <value>SOCIALSCIENCE</value>
                        <value>SONG</value>
                        <value>SONNET</value>
                        <value>SPEECH</value>
                        <value>STAGEREVIEW</value>
                        <value>TESTIMONY</value>
                        <value>TEXTBOOK</value>
                        <value>THEATREOFCRUELTY</value>
                        <value>THEATREOFTHEABSURD</value>
                        <value>THEOLOGY</value>
                        <value>THESAURUS</value>
                        <value>THRILLER</value>
                        <value>TOPOGRAPHICALPOETRY</value>
                        <value>TRACTPAMPHLET</value>
                        <value>TRAGEDY</value>
                        <value>TRAGICOMEDY</value>
                        <value>TRANSLATION</value>
                        <value>TRAVELWRITING</value>
                        <value>TREATISE</value>
                        <value>UTOPIA</value>
                        <value>VERSENOVEL</value>
                        <value>VIGNETTE</value>
                        <value>VILLANELLE</value>
                        <value>YOUNGADULTWRITING</value>
                    </choice>
                </attribute>
            </optional>
            <optional>
                <attribute name="PROPOSEDALTERNATIVENAME"/>
            </optional>
            <text/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="xptr-element">
        <element name="XPTR">
            <!-- LS to MP: No documentation for this. -->
            <ref name="links-content"/>
            <empty/>
        </element>
    </define>

    <define name="links-content">
        <ref name="ID-attribute"/>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="DATE"/>
            <!--CDATA-->
        </optional>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="DOC"/>
            <!-- ENTITY -->
        </optional>
        <attribute name="FROM" a:defaultValue="ROOT">
            <value>ROOT</value>
        </attribute>
        <attribute name="TO" a:defaultValue="DITTO">
            <value>DITTO</value>
        </attribute>
        <ref name="resp-content"/>
        <optional>
            <attribute name="URL"/>
        </optional>
    </define>

    <define name="xref-element">
        <element name="XREF">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">The xref element surounds a url which you wish to make into a hyperlink.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>xref</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The xref element surounds a url which you wish to make into a hyperlink.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Biography</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Events</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>Documentation</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>The xref element has one required attribute, resp. The url attribute must be filles in exactly, including the http and www portions.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>&lt;xref RESP=&quot;SIB&quot; URL=&quot;http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/2374&quot;&lt;&gt;/xref&gt;</xhtml:p>
            <ref name="links-content"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                    <text/>
                    <ref name="address-element"/>
                    <ref name="date-element"/>
                    <ref name="name-element"/>
                    <ref name="rs-element"/>
                    <ref name="time-element"/>
                    <ref name="corr-element"/>
                    <ref name="emph-element"/>
                    <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                    <ref name="soCalled-element"/>
                    <ref name="docTitle-element"/>
                    <ref name="xptr-element"/>
                    <ref name="xref-element"/>
                    <ref name="quote-element"/>
                </choice>
            </zeroOrMore>
        </element>
    </define>

    <!-- Inclusions start -->

    <define name="Div0-inclusion">
        <zeroOrMore>
            <choice>
                <ref name="researchNote-element"/>
                <ref name="title-element"/>
                <ref name="bibCit-element"/>
                <ref name="scholarNote-element"/>
                <ref name="keywordClass-element"/>
                <ref name="bibCits-element"/>
                <ref name="lb-element"/>
            </choice>
        </zeroOrMore>
    </define>

    <define name="Div1-inclusion">
        <zeroOrMore>
            <choice>
                <ref name="name-element"/>
                <ref name="place-element"/>
                <ref name="orgName-element"/>
                <ref name="rs-element"/>
                <ref name="sic-element"/>
                <ref name="corr-element"/>
                <ref name="emph-element"/>
                <ref name="quote-element"/>
                <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                <ref name="soCalled-element"/>
                <ref name="topic-element"/>
                <ref name="tGenre-element"/>
                <ref name="job-element"/>
                <ref name="xptr-element"/>
                <ref name="xref-element"/>
            </choice>
        </zeroOrMore>
    </define>

    <define name="narrow-inclusion">
        <!-- Inclusion from Div0 and Div1 except 
        elements in <date>*, keywordClass, name, 
        orgName, place, scholarNote, topic -->
        <zeroOrMore>
            <choice>
                <ref name="researchNote-element"/>
                <ref name="title-element"/>
                <ref name="bibCit-element"/>
                <ref name="bibCits-element"/>
                <ref name="lb-element"/>
                <ref name="rs-element"/>
                <ref name="sic-element"/>
                <ref name="corr-element"/>
                <ref name="emph-element"/>
                <ref name="quote-element"/>
                <ref name="foreign-element"/>
                <ref name="soCalled-element"/>
                <ref name="tGenre-element"/>
                <ref name="xptr-element"/>
                <ref name="xref-element"/>
            </choice>
        </zeroOrMore>
    </define>

    <define name="Div0narrow-inclusion">
        <!-- Inclusion from Div0 except 
            elements in <date>*, keywordClass, name, 
            orgName, place, scholarNote, topic -->
        <zeroOrMore>
            <choice>
                <ref name="researchNote-element"/>
                <ref name="title-element"/>
                <ref name="bibCit-element"/>
                <ref name="bibCits-element"/>
                <ref name="lb-element"/>
            </choice>
        </zeroOrMore>
    </define>

    <!-- common attributes -->

    <define name="ID-attribute">
        <optional>
            <attribute name="ID">
                <!-- LS to MP: No documentation was found for this attribute. -->
                <data type="ID"/>
            </attribute>
        </optional>
    </define>

    <define name="reg-attribute">
        <optional>
            <attribute name="REG" a:documentation="Regularized value"/>
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">reg (or regularization) contains a reading which has been regularized or normalized in some sense.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>reg</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>reg (or regularization) contains a reading which has been regularized or normalized in some sense.</xhtml:p>
        </optional>
    </define>

    <define name="sex-attribute">
        <attribute name="SEX">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">Sex is an attribute applied to the writing document as a whole and specifies whether the author who is the subject of the document is male, female, unknown or transgendered.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>sex</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Sex is an attribute applied to the writing document as a whole and specifies whether the author who is the subject of the document is male, female, unknown or transgendered.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Placement</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Writing</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:p>This attribute is attached to the element Writing, the largest conceptual bucket surrounding an entire writing document. It is placed in the Orlando Header preceding your document. If you receive your writing document as a template, this attribute will already contain a value of "female." Change it if you are working on anyone but a woman writer.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Relationships</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>There are four allowable values attached to this attribute: &quot;male,&quot; &quot;female,&quot; &quot;unknown&quot; and &quot;transgendered.&quot; Use &quot;unknown&quot; in situations where a pseudonym does not direct you to any clues about the author's sex.</xhtml:p>
            <choice>
                <value>FEMALE</value>
                <value>MALE</value>
                <value>UNKNOWN</value>
                <value>TRANSGENDERED</value>
            </choice>
        </attribute>
    </define>

    <define name="person-attribute">
        <attribute name="PERSON">
            <a:documentation xmlns:a="http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0">person provides information about an identifiable individual, for example a participant in a language interaction, or a person referred to in a historical source.</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>person</xhtml:h2>            
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>person provides information about an identifiable individual, for example a participant in a language interaction, or a person referred to in a historical source.</xhtml:p>
            <xhtml:h3>Examples</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p></xhtml:p>
            <choice>
                <value>HISTORICALFIGURE</value>
                <value>WRITER</value>
                <value>BRWWRITER</value>
                <value>IBRWRITER</value>
            </choice>
        </attribute>
    </define>
    
    <define name="standard-attribute">
        <attribute name="STANDARD">
            <a:documentation>Used to record the standard name by which a person,
            organization, or topic is known</a:documentation>
            <xhtml:h2>standard</xhtml:h2>
            <xhtml:h3>Definition</xhtml:h3>
            <xhtml:p>Used to record the standard name by which a person,
                organization, or topic is known</xhtml:p>  
        </attribute>
    </define>
    
    <!-- Entities begin -->

    <!--    <define name="BasicLatinToken">
        <data type="token">
            <param name="pattern">[\p{IsBasicLatin}-[\P{L}]]*</param>
        </data>
    </define>
    
    <define name="GreekToken">
        <data type="token">
            <param name="pattern">[\p{IsGreek}-[\P{L}]]*</param>
        </data>
    </define>
    
    <define name="Latin-1SupplementToken">
        <data type="token">
            <param name="pattern">[\p{IsLatin-1Supplement}-[\P{L}]]*</param>
        </data>
    </define>
    
    <!-\-<define name="LatinExtended-AToken">
        <data type="token">
            <param name="pattern">[\p{IsLatinExtended-A}-[\P{L}]]*</param>
        </data>
    </define>-\->
    
    <define name="LatinExtendedAdditionalToken">
        <data type="token">
            <param name="pattern">[\p{IsLatinExtendedAdditional}-[\P{L}]]*</param>
        </data>
    </define>
    
    <define name="LatinExtended-BToken">
        <data type="token">
            <param name="pattern">[\p{IsLatinExtended-B}-[\P{L}]]*</param>
        </data>
    </define>
    
    <define name="NumberFormsToken">
        <data type="token">
            <param name="pattern">[\p{IsNumberForms}-[\P{L}]]*</param>
        </data>
    </define>-->

</grammar>
